<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Collectanea Out of St. Gregory the Great, and St. Bernard the devout, against the Papists who adhere to the doctrine of the present Church of Rome, in the most fundamentall points betweene them and vs.</title>
            <author>Panke, John.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1618</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 190 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 68 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08888</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19169</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120116</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855316</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855316</idno>
            <idno type="VID">20803</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08888)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20803)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1553:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Collectanea Out of St. Gregory the Great, and St. Bernard the devout, against the Papists who adhere to the doctrine of the present Church of Rome, in the most fundamentall points betweene them and vs.</title>
                  <author>Panke, John.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[22], 113, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Lichfield, and Iames Short, printers to the famous Vniversitie,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1618.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: John Panke.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Gregory --  I, --  Pope, ca. 540-604.</term>
               <term>Bernard, --  of Clairvaux, Saint, 1090 or 91-1153.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:20803:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20803:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>COLLECTANEA.</hi> OVT OF S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> GREGORY THE GREAT, AND S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> BERNARD THE Devout, againſt the Papiſts who ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>here to the doctrine of the preſent Church of Rome, in the moſt fundamentall points betweene them and vs.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>AVG. DE CIV. DEI Lib. 19. Cap. 27.</bibl>
               <p>Iuſtitia noſtra potius conſtat remiſſione peccatorum, quam perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one virtutum.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>AT OXFORD,</hi> Printed by IOHN LICHFIELD, and IAMES SHORT, Printers to the famous Vniverſitie. 1618.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:20803:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20803:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL, HIS VERY GOOD FRIEND, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> GEOROE CHVRCHOVVSE, Maior of the city of <hi>New Sarum</hi> in the County of Wiltes. To <hi>the Iuſtices, and Aldermen his</hi> Aſſiſtants; and the whole <hi>incorporation there:</hi> IOHN PANKE wiſheth the full fruition of <hi>diuine bleſſings, both in this and that other World to come.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Hold it a ground apparant in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon (good M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Maior) that eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry euil is ſo much the greater euill,<note place="margin">Tanto aliquod malum eſt pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jus malum, quanto magis adimit de bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no. Aug.</note> by how much the more it with-draweth from good;
<pb facs="tcp:20803:3"/>from which principle then, may vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly be drawen this following trueth, <hi>That they deſerue ill of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian common wealth, who oppugne the faith by bringing in hereſies, or when brought in by others, defend them, becauſe the foundation being ruinous, it is of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsity, that whatſoeuer is thereupon built doeth fall;</hi> Inſomuch, that the moſt wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt adviſer of mankind, our Lord and Saviour, willed his weake Diſciples to beware of the Leauen of the Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies and Saduces,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.11.</note> which is interpreted to be the doctrine they taught. From all which, thus much will appeare to all men, that they muſt bew are <hi>what, and of whom they heare:</hi> for as it is not poſſible to gather grapes of thornes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.16.</note> or figs of thiſtles, no more is it of new teachers wholeſome doctrine.<note place="margin">Ipſa doctrinae novitas eſt de ſe ſuſpecta, quoniam Chriſtus &amp; Apoſtoli ejus ſufficientem doctrinam ad vitam aeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quendam de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derunt. Et re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctè Tertullia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, Rectum eſt quod om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium eſt pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum, adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinum veró, quod novum eſt &amp; poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us. <hi>Joh.</hi> 20.31. Fides Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lica, quam in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dubiè tenere oportet, eſt ea quam ſacrae literae tradu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. —quas Deus ipſe manibus hominum ſcripſit.</note> As they are new teachers, ſo is their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine noveltie, which euen in it ſelfe is to be ſuſpected, becauſe Chriſt and
<pb facs="tcp:20803:3"/>his Apoſtles deliuered <hi>ſufficient do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine</hi> for the attaining of euerlaſting life: And as the holy Evangeliſt ſaith, <hi>Theſe things are WRITTEN, that ye might beleeue, that Ieſus is that Chriſt that Sonne of God, and that in beleeuing ye might haue life thorough his Name.</hi> Thus is that Catholike faith, which ought vndoubtedly to be held, that which the ſacred Scriptures doe deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer: With theſe we muſt ſight againſt all novell doctrines. Thoſe are the weapons, with which we muſt profli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate and repel all humane inventions, God writing them by the hands of men. All Decrees of Councels, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretals of Popes, Traditions of Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and all Writings elſe whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, muſt giue place to them. The ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scriptures are that <hi>Torrent</hi> or <hi>Brook,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam. L</hi> 7.</note> out of which DAVID tooke the ſtones, with which he ouer-threw the mighty <hi>Goliah;</hi> other teſtimonies
<pb facs="tcp:20803:4"/>without theſe, are as <hi>Sauls</hi> armour, more comberſome, than ſerviceable; as arguments drawen from humane wiſdome: Finally, according to thoſe Bookes of the Scriptures, (ſaith S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi>) we judge frankly of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther writings,<note place="margin">Cont. Creſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con. Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mat. lib. 2. cap. 31.</note> whether they be of the faithfull, or vnfaithfull. Which if it be ſo, there ariſeth yet another maine point to be marked; That where the Scriptures are either locked vp from the people, that they may not exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe them by reading and meditating on them; or where they are neglected &amp; not opened by preaching, through the idleneſſe of Paſtors, there muſt needes appeare groſſe ignorance in thoſe that ought to be taught, and great ſinne remaineth to them which ſhould teach; for thoſe which do not heare, cannot learne; which wanting, preſently that evill enemy the Devill, ever ready to hurt, firſt perverting the
<pb facs="tcp:20803:4"/>affection, and then blinding the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, drawing all men into all errors. This is ſo farre from any poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of gaine-ſaying, that both ſides, I meane, Papiſts and Proteſtants ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe vnto it. And although (God be praiſed for it) that darke eclipſe of the body of the Sunne, doeth not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare in our <hi>Horizon,</hi> (I meane in this famous Church of <hi>England</hi>) yet are there parts beyond the Seas, which ſuffer that darkneſſe, and lye plunged in all thoſe calamities, which are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequents of it.<note place="margin">Contra heareſ: lib. 1. cap. 13.</note> Touching this matter (ſaith <hi>Alphonſus a Caſtro</hi>) our owne Countrey of <hi>Spaine</hi> may miniſter vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs plentifull teſtimonies, in which, not aboue <hi>ten yeeres</hi> ſince,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>citra decem annos.</hi> He wrot this a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the yere <hi>1534.</hi>
               </note> in that part of <hi>Cantabria,</hi> which now is called <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varra,</hi> and <hi>Biſcaya,</hi> amongſt them which inhabite the vplands, ſundry er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors are found, many ſuperſtitions, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers idolatries, inſomuch that they
<pb facs="tcp:20803:5"/>worſhip the Devill himſelfe, appca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring vnto them in forme of a <hi>Goate,</hi> which for certaine is knowne to bee practized by them in ſecret, theſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny yeeres. In which matter there are more weon en than men; for that evil enemie knoweth by the firſt man, that it is eaſier to deceiue a woman than a man, and that ſhe will faſter hold the ill, to which at once ſhe cleaueth. This ſame miſchiefe, though not ſo great wee finde likewiſe in other parts of <hi>Spaine,</hi> in which the word of God is very ſeldome preached; for there are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them many ſuperſtitions, heatheniſh cuſtomes, through no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cauſe appearing, but for want of Preachers. Thus farre he. By which relation, you and all men elſe may ſee the great miſeries that follow the want of the word of God, where true Religion is aſleepe, and the arch-ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my the Devill ruleth the affections,
<pb facs="tcp:20803:5"/>Practize the Word then by often rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.<note place="margin">Lectio lecta placer, decies reperita pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cobit.</note> Be exerciſed in hearing it prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched. By which doing you ſhalbe the better able to diſcerne and judge of all doctrines propounded; for where do you reade in the holy Scriptures, or can you from thence conclude,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> That Lay men (all except the Clergie) ſhould bee debarred from receiuing the Communion in both kindes,<note place="margin">Thinke of theſe points, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire of them.</note> of Bread, and Wine? Or,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> that God euer commaunded <hi>Images</hi> to bee placed in Churches, to the intent they ſhould be worſhipped? Or, that any ſinne,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> as it is ſinne, in its owne nature is <hi>ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall,</hi> and not worthy of eternal death? Or,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> that wicked men miſcreants and vnbeleevers, are true members of the Catholike Church? Or,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> that they in receiving the Sacrament, doe feede v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon, &amp; eate the true Body of Chriſt? Or,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> that there is any fleſhly and orall eating of the naturall Body of Chriſt
<pb facs="tcp:20803:6"/>in the Sacrament. Or, that Ignorance ſhould be the mother of Devotion, that is, the more ignorant, the more devout. Or, that it belongeth to the Pope to graunt Indulgences and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dons to ſinners,<note place="margin">condonando illis poenam ad cuius tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tantiam pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cator obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batur etiam remiſſa culpa.</note> pardoning them the puniſhment, to the enduring where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the offender is bound, even after the fault is forgiuen. For theſe I ſay, and a ſwarme of ſuch new vpſtart do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, thruſt vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you by the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> conſult with the Word of God, contained in the Bookes of the Old and New Teſtament, and you ſhall find no one ſtep leading to them, but all the contrary, ſo neere are they to the curſe that teach the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Touching ſome which points, and divers other maintained againſt vs, by the contrary erring partie, I haue for your further knowledge and inſtruction in this ſmall treatiſe reſted my ſelfe only vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on two famous Doctors of the
<pb facs="tcp:20803:6"/>Church S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Gregory</hi> called the great, ſometime Biſhoppe of Rome, and S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Bernard</hi> another Father though of la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter time, ſhewing that both theſe in many of the maine differences, and ſome of thoſe of hie conſequence, taught the ſame doctrine to their churches &amp; hearers, which the church of England teacheth to hers.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> For the perfection &amp; ſufficiency of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture without tradition.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> In the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of merits, that no workes are meritorious, or worthie of the bliſſe of the life to come.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> That there is no faith without workes, and that faith only inſtifieth.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> That concupiſcence is ſinne in the firſt motions of it.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Of the certainty of ſalvatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the elect.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> That there is no freedome in the will to good and holy actions, except it bee made free.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> Of the frivolous and vaine vſurped title, that the Pope ſhould bee called <hi>Vniverſall Biſhop.</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> That the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike
<pb facs="tcp:20803:7"/>Church which we beleeue in the Creed is the whole company of the elect only.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> Of the impoſſibility for any man how regenerate ſoeuer, to fulfill the law, now in his corrupt na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. That there is no inherent righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> in man, wherby he may be iuſtified before Gods tribunal, but the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt is imputed, being apprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded by Faith. Meditate by reading I pray you vpon theſe pointes, and you ſhall plainly ſee that the contrarie doctrines are at this day taught by the Church of Rome, not ſo much contrarie to vs, as they are to thoſe which were taught formerly in leſſe corrupt times, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the Church of Rome it ſelfe, ſo that it reſteth ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g on our parts to be maintained <hi>That we haue noe otherwiſe departed from the Church of Rome, than Rome hath from it ſelfe.</hi> Gregorie was Pope of Rome a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the yeere of our redemption by
<pb facs="tcp:20803:7"/>Chriſt 600. ſo that whatſoeuer wee ſhall teach and find in him, we and he may well make it good againſt them. If he had his eſcapes &amp; ouerſights in ſome points of Doctrine, according as they were then creeping in, &amp; doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully held, being of leſſe moment and waight than thoſe before mentioned; &amp; law no further cauſe of diſſiking or diſallowing them, than that time af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forded him, in his owne iudgment: as we may not ioine with him, in the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending of them; ſo are we not willing to giue any hard or vniuſt cen ſure touching his perſon for teaching them; But leauing both the builder, &amp; that which he builded to their owne Maſter to ſtand or to fall, we are hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly to thank our great God for direc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting his knowledg ſuch that it kept the maine foundation by Ieſus Chriſt. Ch how ſweetly doeth he ſing that Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel-like ſong! <hi>The felicitie of the Saints
<pb facs="tcp:20803:8"/>is mercy God re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dreth according to works,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mercy, not workes. Not for works.</note> 
               <hi>though not for the workes. To that bleſſed life wherein we ſhall line with God and of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Our labour is not worthy our glory.</note> 
               <hi>no labour can be equalled, no workes can be compared. Our iust aduocate will in iudgment defend vs for iuſt, becauſe wee know and accuſe our ſelues to be vniuſt.</hi> Know you this readers, that this is <hi>Gregories</hi> doctrine, and you will not know the doctrine of the Councel of <hi>Trent,</hi> ſome 60. yeres ſince eſtabliſh'd, and now held and maintained by <hi>Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus Quintus</hi> the now Pope. S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Bernard</hi> the other Doctor propoſed, liued in a time far more corrupt, yet ſtill held &amp; preached the maine points that wee doe. He was (ſaith Biſhop <hi>Iuell</hi>) a Monk,<note place="margin">anno Domini 1117. <hi>about</hi> 500. <hi>yeeres ſince.</hi> Iuel. art. 21. diviſ. 8.</note> &amp; lived at Claravallis in France about the ſame time that Thomas Becket liued in England. At which time, as it appeareth by his often co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints the Church of God was miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably defaced. For thus hee writeth,
<pb facs="tcp:20803:8"/>namely touching the Cleargie of Rome, <hi>Nihil integri eſt in Clero &amp;c.</hi> In the whole Cleargie (wherein hee concludeth the Pope,<note place="margin">In Pſalm. Qui habitat.</note> the Cardinalls, the Biſhops, and all the reſt) there is no part left ſound. It remaineth now that the man of ſinne,<note place="margin">De converfio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne Pauli.</note> that is Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, be revealed. From the toppe to the toe, there is no health. The ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of Chriſt, now ſerue Antichriſt.<note place="margin">In Cant. Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tic.</note> Therefore Bernard, living in a time of ſuch corruption, and being carried a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with the violence and tempeſt of the ſame, muſt needs in ſome things not ſee all. The moſt reverend Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop that now is,<note place="margin">In his Graces anſwere to D. Hill. reaſ. <hi>1. § 30.</hi> pag. <hi>60.61.</hi> and reaſ. <hi>5. §. 28</hi>
               </note> ſaith thus alſo of him. Although hee ſaw not all things yet we finde in him <hi>ſaniorem partem</hi> a liberall profeſſion of many good and ſound points agreeable to the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell. Touching the matter of merit by good workes, for iuſtification by faith alone in Chriſt, for freewill, for cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
<pb facs="tcp:20803:9"/>aſſurance of ſalvation in the death and by the ſtrength of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, and for diſliking then the vile life of the Cleargie, how cleare, how pregnant, how copious is he? Theſe things wee teach together with him, and notwithſtanding his other ſlipps, we doubt not but his ſoule is with the Lord. He held the foundation by on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly faith in Chriſt, and that our beſt deeds are but <hi>via regni, non cauſa reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nandi.</hi> The way to the kingdome, not the cauſe of raigning.<note place="margin">Digreſſ. 43. §. 42. pag. 298.</note> D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> White in his Treatiſe of the way to the true Church, ſaith Bernard knewe not the preſent Romane faith. Hee was a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt in none of the principall points of the religion. Hee held the ſufficiencie of the Scripture without traditions. Iuſtification by faith alone. That our workes merit not. That no man can keepe the law. That a man, by the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonie of Gods ſpirit within him,
<pb facs="tcp:20803:9"/>may be certaine of Grace. That there is no ſuch freewill as the popiſh ſchoolemen teach. Theſe, and ſuch o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther teſtimonies haue theſe worthie pillers of our Church giuen, vnto that worthie and religious man Bernard. The places touching theſe points al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaged, you ſhal finde quoted at large by me, tranſcribed by my paines out of his owne workes, as they lie word for word, led there vnto by the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned workes, eſpecially of your late right Reverend Biſhop in his ſeverall writings againſt D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Biſhop; touching whom, ſince it did pleaſe God to call him ſo ſoone from you, I will ſay no more at this time but as <hi>Salomo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> ſaith:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 10.7.</note> 
               <hi>The memoriall of the iuſt ſhall bee bleſſed;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 112.16.</note> 
               <hi>and the righteous ſhall be had in an ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting remembrance;</hi> And for your parts carry about with you this ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of the wiſe man.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sapient.</hi> 4.13.</note> 
               <hi>That though he departed from you ſoone, yet fulfilled he
<pb facs="tcp:20803:10"/>much time:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Oſtende<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris nunc tantu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fata, neque vl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra eſſe ſinent. Aeneid. lib. 6.</note> God as it were but ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him vnto you, &amp; then taking him away. The learned paines alſo taken by D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Morton, the reverend Biſhop of Cheſter in his treatiſe called the <hi>Protestants appeale,</hi> I haue vſed herein. Which two, haue for you and me, &amp; all men elſe of our condition, trode ſuch a beaten path, that it leadeth to the diſcovery of all the by-waies in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented by the Church of Rome to hide that truth, which the Church of God hath ever found in the holy Scriptures, Councells, and Fathers, to the depreſſing of hereſies. O bleſſed Bernard,<note place="margin">Obſerue Bern: Spirit.</note> the ſpirit of God taught thee to teach, That eternall life is purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by no merits, but is freely giuen. That the merits of men are ſuch, that life everlaſting is not due for them by right; or that God ſhould bee ſaid to doe iniurie, except hee yeeld it them. Surely (ſaith hee) whatſoever is want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:20803:10"/>to me of my ſelfe, I boldly take it vnto mee out of the bowels of my Lord, becauſe they flowe out with mercy. My merit is the Lords mercy. Read O man in thine owne hart, read within thy ſelfe concerning thy ſelfe, the witnes of truth, <hi>&amp; thou wilt iudge thy ſelfe vnworthy of commonlight.</hi> Theſe and ſuch other ſpake devout <hi>Bernard,</hi> but ſay the Papiſts ſo? No, they write in a more loftie ſtile, they ſcorne intreatie or ſupplication. The Rhemiſts in their Annotations on the new Teſtament,<note place="margin">Annot. in Mat. <hi>6.</hi> v. <hi>4.</hi> in Marc. <hi>12.</hi> v. <hi>21.</hi> in Ro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <hi>2.</hi> v. <hi>6.</hi> in Cor. <hi>3.</hi> v. <hi>8.</hi> &amp; in Tim. Epiſt. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>4.</hi> v. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> doe nothing ſo much as contrary this doctrine, pleading their workes to bee meritorious. Workes (ſay they) are the very cauſe of ſalvation, and fully worthie of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting life.<note place="margin">Obſerue the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of theſe men.</note> The ioyes of heauen is the hire, wages for workes, which workes can bee no other, then the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lure, deſert, price, worth, and merit of the ſame. Againe, Heaven is our own
<pb facs="tcp:20803:11"/>right, bargained, and wrought for, &amp; accordingly paid vnto vs, as our hire at the day of iudgement. Marke theſe, and tell me, whether there can be any greater oppoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. It ſufficeth for me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit (ſaith Bernard) to knowe that me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits are not ſufficient; nay, ſay the Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts. Know that good workes are ſo farre meritorious,<note place="margin">Annot. in Hebr. <hi>6.</hi> v. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> that God ſhould be vniuſt if he rendred not heauen for the ſame. Is this agreement with the Doctors and ancient Church? O no beloued, they are ſeducers that teach ſuch doctrine, and ſeduced are they that harken vnto them. Thus much I now thought good to ſay, to giue you ſome light, before you enter to reade the whole. Marke and obſerue the margent notes with the text, and you ſhall diſcouer a number of blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies vttered by them againſt the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie of GOD, as though they were men that knowe none of the mercies
<pb facs="tcp:20803:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>of God in Chriſt; or if they doe know them, as if they needed them not, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſh, as if they were aſhamed to acknowledge them, a doctrine of the deviſe of their owne braine, as full of pride one way as it is of feare, anxiety, and doubt another way. J may not in this bee tedious vnto you, deſirous to ende this ſpeech I heartely pray the God of heauen to powre into your hearts the true feeling of all holy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in the holy Ghoſt; and multiplie his temporall bleſſings vpon you and yours, make your affaires quiet and peaceable to the increaſe of your out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward welfare; ſo to liue, that you feare God, and honour the King.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>From the Cloſe at Sarum <date>this 24 <hi>Iunij.</hi> 1618.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Yours in all loue, <hi>JOHN PANKE.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="Gregory the Great" type="patristic_quotations">
            <pb facs="tcp:20803:12"/>
            <head>AN HVNDRED TE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STIMONIES OF SAINT GREGORIE the Great, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time <hi>Biſhop of Rome, ſhewing</hi> that in all and every of them, he a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeth with the Proteſtants, <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the doctrine now taught by his following ſucceſſors, the Biſhope of Rome.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>§ I.</hi> What is meant by the Rocke. <hi>MAT. 16.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N Petra Eccleſiae, hoc eſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lib. 3. Epiſt. 33.</note> 
                  <hi>in confeſſione beati Petri.</hi> In the rock of the church, that is, in the confeſſion of <hi>Peter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tu es Petrus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In 5. Pſal. poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit. in illa ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba, Initio tu Domine ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram fundaſti. <hi>By Ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ke is meant Chriſt. They ſay Peter, and then the Pope.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>&amp; ſuper hanc Petram aedificabo Eccleſiam) Ipſe eſt enim Petra, à qua Petrus nomen accepit, &amp; ſuper quam Eccleſiam ſe aedificaturum di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xit.</hi> Thou art <hi>Peter,</hi> and vpon this Rocke will I build my Church. For hee is the Rocke, from whence <hi>Peter</hi> received his name, and vpon whom hee ſaid he would
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:20803:13"/>build his Church.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In ſacriloquio quandò in ſingulari nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mero fundamentum dicitur,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib. 28. in c. 38. Iob. c. 6.</hi> Chriſt the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation. They ſay Peter, and then the Pope.</note> 
                  <hi>nullus alius niſi Chriſtus deſignatur.</hi> Whereſoeuer in holy Scripture, this word Foundation is found in the ſingular number, it ſignifieth Chriſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>§. 2.</hi> Perfection and ſufficiency of the Scripture.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>id cor &amp; animam Dei niſi ſacram eius Scripturam accipimus.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>In 1. Reg. l. 2. c. 3. Mor. l. c. 16.</hi> The holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture containeth the minde of God to vs. <hi>Ibid. lib. 18. cap. 14.</hi> All doctrine muſt be confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by Scripture.</note> 
                  <hi>Per eam Deus loquitur omne quod vult.</hi> What is the holy Scripture but the Heart &amp; Soule of God; by it God ſpeaketh all that hee will.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eos ad ſacrae authoritatis paginas vocat, ut ſi verè loqui deſiderent, indè ſumere de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beant quid loquantur, &amp;c.</hi> He calleth them to the Bookes of the holy Scripture, ſo that he that deſireth to ſpeake or preach truly, muſt take from thence that which he ſpeaketh, and fetch the grounds of his matters, out of the ſacred Bookes, that he may bring all that he ſpeaketh, to the foundation of divine authority, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:20803:13"/>ſettle the buildings of his ſpeech.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sancti viri ſe conſilijs Scripturae ex toto addicunt, ut videlicet nihil agant,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>In Cant. cap. 5. &amp; in Ezech. hom. 15. &amp; 9.</hi> All matters concerning faith and godlineſſe are conteined in the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. They ſay, we muſt look for a part thereof in traditions. All our armour againſt our ghoſtly enemies.</note> 
                  <hi>niſi quod ex responſo Scripturaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> audiunt, &amp;c.</hi> Holy men doe wholly addict themſelues to the counſels or directions of the Scripture, namely ſo as to doe nothing, but they heare by aunſwere of the Scripture, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of whatſoeuer doubts, aduice is ſought for in the Scripture, it is there fully found, of all things without exception. And all our munition or armour, yea all things that doe edifie, all things that doe inſtruct, are contained therein.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>§ 3.</hi> No merit in this life, but death.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>IVsti perituros ſe abſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ambiguitate prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciunt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Moral. lib. 8. cap. 9.</hi> No meriting of heaven by man. They ſay, yes, by good workes.</note> 
                  <hi>ſi remotapietate iudicentur, &amp;c.</hi> The juſt doe know before-hand, that they ſhall periſh without doubt, if God ſet mercy aſide in the judging of them, becauſe even that which ſeemeth our juſt life is but ſinne, if Gods mercy when hee judgeth it, doe not excuſe the ſame.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quod ſi illa ſanctorum foelicitas miſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordia
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:20803:14"/>eſt,<note place="margin">In Pſalm. poenit. 7.</note> &amp; non merit is acquiritur, ubi e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit quod ſcriptum eſt, &amp; tu reddes unicui<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>, ſecundum opera ſua?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eternall life is mercy only, and is not to be purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed or gained by merits.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp;c.</hi> If the felicity of the Saints be mercy, and be not obteined by merits, how ſhall that ſtand that is written, <hi>Thou ſhalt render vnto euery man according to his workes?</hi> If it bee rendred according to workes, how ſhall it bee e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed mercy?<note place="margin">The Papiſts mocke at this diſtinction in vs: but bluſh at it in Gregory.</note> But it is one thing to re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der according to workes; and another thing to render for the works themſelues. For in that it is ſaid, according to works, the very quality of the workes is vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, ſo as that whoſe good workes ſhal appeare, his reward ſhalbe glorious. For to that bleſſed life wherein we ſhall liue with God, and of God, no labour can bee equalied,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>In Ezechiel, hom. 7.</hi> O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>riuſtice is the imputation of iuſtice or righteouſneſſe without works: for we know &amp; confeſſe our ſelues to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſt as touching workes.</note> no workes can be compared, for that the Apoſtle telleth vs. The ſufferings of this time are not comparable in worth to the glory to come, that ſhall be revei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led on vs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iustus Advocatus noſter justos nos de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendet in judicio, quia noſmetipſos &amp; cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſcimus &amp; accuſamus injuſtos. Non ergo in fletibus, non in actibus nostris, ſed in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocati noſtri allogatione confidamus.</hi> Our
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:20803:14"/>juſt Advocate, will in judgement defend vs for juſt, becauſe wee know and accuſe our ſelues to be vnjuſt: and therefore let vs not put confidence in our teares, or in our workes, but in our Advocates allega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or interceſſion for vs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>§ <hi>4.</hi> No true faith without workes.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>In Ezech. hom. 22.</hi> No ſeparation betweene Faith and Workes ſaith Gregory: yes, ſay they, a man may haue true faith, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out good workes. The true name of Faith is not appliable, where there is not Charity ioyned with it, neither can there be true beliefe.</note>
                  <hi>FIdem, spem, charitatem, atque operatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem quamdiu in hac vita vivimus ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quales ſibi eſſe apud nosmetipſos invenimus. &amp;c.</hi> We finde that faith, hope, charitie, &amp; good workes, ſo long as here we liue are equall in vs: For looke how much we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, ſo much alſo we loue, and how much we loue, ſo much wee preſume of hope: Of faith and workes alſo, S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> confeſſeth, ſaying, He that ſaith, he know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth God, and keepeth not his Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements, is a lyar. For the knowledge of God appertaineth to faith, the keeping of the Commandements to workes. When therefore power and time, and place of working ſerueth, ſo much doth a man worke, as he knoweth God, and ſo much
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:20803:15"/>doth he ſhew himſelfe to knowe God,<note place="margin">where there is no loue. Juſtification before God, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth not in proceeding from Faith to Works, but in the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuation of Faith to Faith, yet this Faith cannot be ſeparated from Charity and good Workes.</note> as he worketh good things for Gods ſake. Every one that is converſant in the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of this life, beleeueth ſo much as hee hopeth, and loueth; and looke how much he beleeueth, hopeth, loueth, ſo much hee worketh.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <head>§. <hi>5.</hi> Concupiſcence is ſinne in the first motions of it.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Moral. lib. 14. c. 9.</hi> Concupiſcence or Luſt is ſin, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen in the very habit, or firſt motions of it.</note>
                  <hi>ROm.</hi> 6.12. Let not ſinne raign in your mortall bodies, that yee ſhould there vnto obey by the luſt of it. <hi>Non ait non ſit, ſed non regnet, quia non eſſe non poteſt, non autem regnare in cordibus bonorum po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt.</hi> The Apoſtle ſaith not, let it not bee, but let it not raigne, becauſe it ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not but be, but it may be without a kingdome in the hearts of good men.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Moral. lib. 21. cap. 3.</hi> The motion or ſting of concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcence, which is heere called vnlawfull de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire or luſt can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bee avoyded of the Faithfull in this life, yet hath it not do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion ouer them, ſo that that motion or ſting, euen the very temptation of Sin is Sin in vs, but without dominion. But contrary to this heere of Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, do they teach, that concupiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence is not Sin properly, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly called ſo by the Scripture. <hi>Mor. lib: 18. c. 5.</hi> Evill cogitation before conſent, and without conſent is ſinne. They ſay no, not before conſent come. To decline in thought is to fal into ſinne.</note> And againe. <hi>Pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catum in mortali corpore non eſſe, ſed reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nare probibuit, quia in carne corruptibili non regnare poteſt, ſed non eſſe non potest.</hi> The Apoſtle for biddeth not ſin to be, but not to raigne in our mortall bodie, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:20803:15"/>it may be without raigning in cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible fleſh, but it cannot but be there. For even to bee tempted of ſinne, is ſinne vnto it; which becauſe we cannot bee al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together without ſo long as we liue here, the holy preaching<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for that it cannot ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly expell and driue it out, taketh away from it the kingdome out of the habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our hearts, that albeit vnlawfull deſire, as a theefe doe privily thruſt in it ſelfe many times amongſt our good thoughts, though it enter into vs, yet may not haue dominion ouer vs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sciendum eſt quod ſunt peccata quae à iuſtis vitari poſſunt, &amp; ſunt nonnulla quae etiam à iuſtis vitari non poſſunt. &amp;c.</hi> Wee are to know, that there are ſinnes which the iuſt may avoid, and there are ſinnes which cannot be avoided in them. For whoſe heart is their abiding in this cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible fleſh that doth not fall by ſini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter thought, though he be not drowned ſo farre as to the pit of conſent: and yet the very cogitation of evill things is ſin, albeit whileſt the cogitation is reſiſted, the minde is deliuered from its own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion. The mind therefore of the iuſt, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:20803:16"/>it bee free from evill worke, yet ſometime falleth by evill thought; it fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth into ſinne, becauſe there is a decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, at leaſt in thought, and yet it hath not whence afterwards with teares to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue it ſelfe, becauſe it firſt recouereth it ſelfe, before it fall by conſent.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">In <hi>1.</hi> reg. l. <hi>6.</hi> c. <hi>2. prope finem.</hi> Here is the root, originall ſin ſtill dwelling and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biding in vs, and the motion of the fleſh, the imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate effect there of it ſelf alſo ſin. They teach con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, that origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſinne doth not remain after baptiſme; and alſo that that which remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth is no ſinne.</note>
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.17. Now it is not I that doe it, but ſinne that dwelleth in me. <hi>Peccatum, quod ſe non operari perhibuit motum car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis intellexit; Peccatum autem in ſe inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans originalem culpam &amp;c.</hi> By the ſinne (ſaith <hi>Gregory</hi>) which the Apoſtle ſaith he worketh not, hee meaneth the motion of the fleſh; and by ſinne dwelling in him he meaneth originall ſinne; and of origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſinne is cauſed the ſinne of the motio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the fleſh; that ſinne continuing in vs, cannot now by the power of any teacher be deſtroyed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.5. Behold I was ſhapen in ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie, and in ſinne hath my mother con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued me. <hi>Nam cum Propheta dicat ecce in iniquitatibus &amp;c.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In Evang. hom. <hi>3</hi> Wee are not in the world with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the ſinne, we brought into the world.</note> 
                  <hi>Sine culpa in mundo eſſe non potuit, qui in mundum cum culpa venit.</hi> The Prophet (ſaith Gregory) could not be without ſinne in this world, who
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:20803:16"/>came with ſinne into the world; and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poundeth his words to this effect. <hi>Opus eſt domine vt miſerearis quia ab ineunte vitae primor dio in peccati foveam incidi,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In Pſal. poenit. <hi>4.</hi> We haue ſtil that remaining in vs for which wee must craue par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don at Gods hands. How tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth the church of Rome now: that in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate there is nothing that God hateth; nothing to ſtay them fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> entring into hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp; concupiſcentiae carnalis ſordibus inquinata nativitatis meae initia contraxi.</hi> Lord I haue need that thou haue mercy vpon me becauſe even from the beginning of my life, I am fallen into the pit of ſinne, and haue drawne my firſt breath, defiled with the vncleaneſſe of carnall concupiſcence, not only that iniquitie which I haue late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly committed abideth in me; I haue alſo in me for thee to pardon of the iniquity of old.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <head>§. <hi>6.</hi> The certaintie of ſalvation in the elect.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Mor. lib. <hi>28.</hi> c. <hi>7.</hi> The ſpirit of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doption giueth witneſſe to the faithfull, that they are the ſons of God.</note>
                  <hi>INter haec etiam qui redemit, non relin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit &amp;c. Novit enim conditor noſter quando exurgere perſecutionis procellam ſinat, quando exurgentem reprimat &amp;c.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midſt perſecutions (ſaith <hi>Gregory</hi> vpon 1. Cor. 10.13.) he that hath redeemed vs, doth not forſake vs, our creator knoweth when to ſuffer the ſtorme to ariſe, &amp; whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:20803:17"/>to ſtay it from riſing. Hee knoweth how to reſtraine that for our ſafegard,<note place="margin">Ibid. l. <hi>29.</hi> c. <hi>12.</hi> Againſt the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certainety of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation. But they teach that the holy ſpirit doth not beare vs witnes abſolutely and aſſuredly, that we are the ſonnes of God, but vnder a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition which is not certain viz. if wee continue ſuffering.</note> which he ſuffereth for the exerciſing of vs to go forth againſt vs, that the raging ſtorme may waſh vs, and not drowne vs. Againe, God ſo diſpenſeth &amp; ordereth (ſaith he) the temptations of the adverſarie, as that they come not too many at once, or that thoſe onely which may bee borne, doe touch the ſoule which God hath inlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, that albe it by the heat of the touch thereof they torment vs, yet they may not by burning waſt and conſume vs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Propheta intuens tantos hoc Eccleſia tempore specie tenus credere quantos nimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum certum eſt electorum numerum ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> tranſire &amp;c. Etiam hiad fidem ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie tenus regniveniunt.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ibid. l. <hi>25.</hi> cap <hi>8.</hi> They that fall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way though in respect of out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſhew and profeſſion they be ſaid for a time to beleeue, yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe their faith hath no roote, they never haue true faith.</note> The Prophet per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued ſo many in this time of the church to beleeue only in ſhew, that verily they paſſed the number of the elect; For they who are not of the number of the elect, doe beleeue bur in ſhew, and come to the faith of the kingdome in ſhewe. And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine. <hi>Aurum quod pravis eius perſuaſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus ſterni quaſi lutum potuerit, aurum antè Dei oculos nunquam fuie.</hi> The gold,<note place="margin">Ibid. l. <hi>34.</hi> c. <hi>13.</hi> We muſt not aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure our ſeluer only by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of outward cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, but the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance muſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe from the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect and teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of inward grace.</note>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:20803:17"/>which by Sathans wicked ſuggeſtions, commeth to bee troden vnder foote like dirt, was never gold in gods ſight; For they that can be ſeduced never to returne againe, ſeeme to looſe holineſſe which they had after a ſort before the eies of men, but indeed never had it in the ſight of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quorum caſus vtilitate non modica ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorum profectibus ſeruit,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mor. l. <hi>34.</hi> c. <hi>13.</hi> When we ſee the falls of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that fall away we are moued thereby not to truſt in our ſelues but to depend vpon God only.</note> 
                  <hi>quia illorum lap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum dum conſpiciunt de ſuo statu contre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſcunt &amp; ruina quae illos damnat iſtos hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliat, &amp;c.</hi> The fall of which (worldlings, or carnall men) yeeldeth no ſmall benefit for the furtherance of the elect, becauſe while they ſee the fall of them they trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble as touching their owne eſtate, &amp; the ruine which condemneth the one, is the humiliation of the other. For they learne to truſt in the defence of him who help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aboue,<note place="margin">In <hi>1.</hi> Reg. lib. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>1.</hi> moral. This is the aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the faithfull, even an vndoubted beleefe, and knowledge that the heavenly ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie is theirs.</note> whilſt they ſee others fall by reſting on their owne ſtrength.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quam familiariter diligit, ſuam eſſe indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hitanter credit; ſuam nam<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> hanc civitatem eſſe cognoverat quidicebat, ſcimus quia ſi terreſtris noſtra domus &amp;c.</hi> Which heave<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly citie Ieruſalem, which is aboue, who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:20803:18"/>intirely loueth, doth vndoubtedly beleeue it is his owne; for hee knewe this citie to be his that ſaid, we knowe that if our earthly houſe of this habitation bee diſſolued, we haue a building which is of God, a houſe not made with hands eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall in heauen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <head>§. <hi>7.</hi> The good works and ſufferings of this life are not meritorious,<note place="margin">The like is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions of merit. § <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> or worthy of the bleſſe of the life to come.</head>
               <p>A <hi>Pud eum diſtrictè iudicati, ipſi quoqui maculas inquinationis habent, quiper munditiam ſanctitatis lucent.</hi> Even they who ſhine in puritie of holineſſe,<note place="margin">Our merit is the Lords ſhewing mercy.</note> haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo their ſpots of filthineſſe, if they bee ſtrictly and narrowly iudged.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quantalibet iuſtitia polleant,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ibid. cap. <hi>21.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>ne quaqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſibi ad innocentiam vel electi ſufficiant, ſi in indicio diſtricte requira<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tur.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Papiſts now talke of nothing ſo much, as of meriting or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feruing of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. Ibid. l. <hi>9.</hi> c. <hi>18.</hi> Heauen is the reward, hire, &amp; repaiment for good workes ſay they. No, ſaith Gregory, whom will yee beleeue.</note> The very elect howſoever they exell in righteouſneſſe, haue not ſufficient in them for innocency if in iudgement they bee ſtrictly dealt withall.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Siremota pietate diſcutimur, opus no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strum
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:20803:18"/>poena dignum eſt, quod nos remune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rari praeſtolamur. Reſtat vt post quam bonu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> opus agitur lachrymae expiationis exquira<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur quatenus ad aeterna praemia meritum recti operis ſubvehat humilias poſtulation<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis.</hi> If wee bee iudged without mercy,<note place="margin">Mans workes done by Chriſts grace, doe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignly, or wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thely deſerue e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall ioy. No, ſaith Gregory, our beſt workes are worthie to be puniſhed, and ſubiect to periſh if God deale ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely &amp; ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with vs. If a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midſt our good workes, it be by humble prayer and requeſt that wee obtaine the eternal reward? what religion haue the Papiſts that plead for the worthines of our works? and deride vs when we ſay that our good workes are not worthy of the glory that is to come. Ibid. l. <hi>9.</hi> cap. <hi>11.</hi> for Iob. Ibid. in Pſalm. poenit <hi>1.</hi> for David,</note> our worke is worthie of puniſhment; which we exſpect to haue rewarded, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the teares of expiation are to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, that humility of prayer may lift vp the merit of good worke to the obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of everlaſting reward. And to the ſame effect hee maketh the holy man <hi>Iob</hi> to ſay, <hi>Et ſi ad opus virtutis excrevero, ad vitam non ex meritis ſed ex venia conva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſco.</hi> Albeit I growe to the worke of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, yet I availe not to life by merits, but by pardon and favour. And ſo he bringeth in <hi>David,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Non de meis meritis con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidens vt me falvum facias ſupplico, ſed de ſola miſericordia tua praeſumens impetrare quod miſericordia tua praeſumens impetrare quod de meis meritis non ſpero.</hi> I pray thee to ſaue me, not truſting in my owne me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, but preſuming to obtaine that of thy
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:20803:19"/>mercy only, which I haue no hope of by my owne merits.</p>
               <p>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Mot. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>17.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>Quid eſt quod in hac vita ſine quavis tenuiſſimi contagij iniquitate peragatur?</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">Lib. <hi>31.</hi> Cap. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Electi quamdiu in hac vita ſunt ſine quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulocun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> culpae contagio eſſe non poſſunt.</hi>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 32. <hi>cap.</hi> 4.</note> 
                  <hi>Nullus in hac vita ita perfectus eſt vt quamlibet Deo devotus ſit, inter ipſa quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumcun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> pia vota non peccet.</hi>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 35. <hi>cap.</hi> 16</note> 
                  <hi>Si de his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinitus diſtricte diſcutimur, quis inter iſta remanet ſalutis locus quando &amp; mala ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtra pura mala ſunt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">If our good works cannot be purely good, if all that we doe be pollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and defiled with the conta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion of ſinne, if God by the eye of his ſevere iudgement doe ſtrictly view and behold the ſame, then cannot any good workes of ours bee truely ſaid to bee wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly glory. Bernard de grat. &amp; lib. arbit. in fine.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp; bona quae nos habere credimus pura bona eſſe nequaqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> poſſunt?</hi> What is there that can bee done in this life, without ſome defilement of ſecret contagion? The elect ſo long as they are in this life cannot be without ſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagion of ſinne. There is none ſo perfect in this life howſoeuer devoted vnto God, that doth not ſinne amidſt his moſt holy and religious deſires. If God doe narrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſift our doings, what place is there left for ſalvation, when our evill doings are meerely evill, but the good things we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue we haue, cannot be purely good.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8. <hi>Henceforth is laid vp for me a crowne of iuſtice, which God that iuſt
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:20803:19"/>iudge will render vnto me at that day. Eſt ergo quam Paulus expectat corona iuſtitiae,<note place="margin">Contrary to this, doth the Church of Rome now teach ſaying, that if God as a juſt iudge ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ioyes of heauen as a crowne of iuſtice then were they before iuſtly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued, and the ſuffering of them that deſerued them were in iuſt proportion worthy of them. Is not this wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy doctrine? Greg. Mor. l. <hi>24.</hi> cap. <hi>5.</hi>
                     </note> ſed iuſtitiae Dei non ſuae; Iuſtum est quippe, vt reddat quod debet. Debet autem quod pollicitus eſt, &amp; hac eſt iuſtitia, de qua prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumit Apoſtolus, promiſſio Dei.</hi> It is a crowne of Iuſtice which S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Paul</hi> expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, but of Gods iuſtice, not his owne; For it is iuſt that God pay that which he ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, and he oweth that which hee promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, and this is the Iuſtice whereof the Apoſtle preſumeth, even the promiſe of God. Againe. <hi>Iuſtitiae noſtra dicitur, non quae ex noſtro noſtra eſt ſed quae divina lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitate fit noſtra.</hi> It is called our inſtice (ſaith <hi>Gregory</hi>) not which is not ours as of our owne, but which by the gift of God be commeth ours.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Qui nihil boni ſibi, ſed toutum gratiae Dei tribuunt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In crowning our iuſtice, it is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified which is ſaid in holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: Hee crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth thee in mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and louing kindneſſe. In Pſalm Poenit. <hi>7.</hi> It is not grace that doth all, ſay the Papiſts now. The iuſt doe attribute all to grace, faith Gregory.</note> 
                  <hi>ſcientes ſe nihil habere quod non acceperunt; hac enim operatus eſt in eis, is qui vaſa miſericordiae fecit eos.</hi> The elect and faithful attribute no good to themſelues, but all wholy to the grace of God; know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that they haue nothing that they
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:20803:20"/>haue not receaued, for hee hath wrought it in them, who hath made them veſſells of his mercy.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Praeveniens gratia liberum in eo arbitri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um focerat in bono,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In Ezec hom. <hi>9.</hi> This did Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſpeake of S. Paule, and the ſame is true in vs.</note> 
                  <hi>libero arbitrio eandem gratiam eſt ſubſecutus in opere.</hi> The preventing grace of God maketh the will free in that that is good, &amp; then we by free will doe in worke followe the ſame grace.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>§. 8.</hi> There is no freedome in the will, to good &amp; holy actions, except it be made free.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>SVperna pietas prius agit in nobis aliquid ſine nobis,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Greg. Mor. lib. <hi>16.</hi> cap. <hi>10.</hi> We haue no pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in nature to follow when grace doth lead. Idem. ibid. When God by converſion hath reformed our wil and wrought in vs the loue of righteouſneſſe, we by this work of grace in vs doe thenceforth apply our ſelues to worke with grace, and the worke that wee do is Gods work and it is our worke, yet no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe ours but that by the gift of God it is wrought in vs, and ſo becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth ours.</note> 
                  <hi>vt ſubſequente quo<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> noſtro libero arbitrio bonum quod iam appetimus agat nobiſcum.</hi> The heavenly grace doth firſt of all without vs worke ſomewhat in vs that our freewill following, he may do with vs that good, wherevnto wee are now become willing.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Divina nos bonit as vt innocentes faciat praevenit, eandem gratiam noſtrum liberum arbitrium ſequitur.</hi> The goodnes of God preventeth vs to make vs innocent, and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:20803:20"/>our freewill followeth the ſame grace.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quod verba praedicationis Dei ab auri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus ad corda deſcendunt, ſolo divino mune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re agitur &amp;c. Per internam gratiam ſolus omnipotens Deus praedicantium verbis ad corda audientium inviſibiliter aditum prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtat.</hi> Inſomuch that the words of the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher, doe deſcend from the eare to the heart, it commeth to paſſe by the onely gift of God who by inward grace inviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly giueth paſſage for the wordes of the preacher to the harts of them that heare.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ipſa perfectio noſtra culpa non caret niſi hanc ſeverus iudex in ſubtili lance exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis miſericorditer penſet.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mor. lib. <hi>5.</hi> cap. <hi>9</hi> All our righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe if it bee narrowly ſifted, is found vniuſt, and defective.</note> Our very perfec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is not free from blame, vnieſſe God in the preciſe ballance of his merciful ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination do mercifully weigh the ſame.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>§. 9.</hi> Our righteouſneſſe is Chriſts righteouſneſſe.<note place="margin">Mor. lib. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>11.</hi> The righteouſnes of the law, is not fulfilled in vs, but vpon our true repentance, God reputeth vs innocent for Chriſts ſake</note>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>PEr hoc cuncta iuſtificat quod eum qui ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne peccato eſt pro peccatoribus damnat.</hi> God through Chriſt doth iuſtifie vs, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe for vs ſinners, hee condemned him
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:20803:21"/>who was without ſinne.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iuſtus advocatus noſter iuſtos nos defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>det in iudicio quia noſmet ipſos &amp; cognoſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus &amp; accuſamus iniuſtos.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In Ezec. hom. <hi>7.</hi> idem in Evang. hom. <hi>25.</hi> The Papiſts now ſpeake of a righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent: which Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory never thought of.</note> 
                  <hi>Paratus eſt De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us poenitentiam nostram nobis ad innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam deputare.</hi> Our iuſt advocate will in iudgement defend vs for iuſt, if we know and accuſe our ſelues to be vniuſt; God being ready for his ſonnes ſake to repute vnto vs our penitency for innocencie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>§. 10.</hi> Faith excludeth not all feare and doubt.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>FIdes ipſa quae ad bona alia capeſcenda nos imbuit,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mor. l. <hi>22.</hi> c. <hi>14.</hi> There may bee a godly feare which is a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſt of our ſelues but the godly cannot haue a doubtfull feare which is diſtruſt full of God.</note> 
                  <hi>plerunque in exordijs ſuis nutat &amp; ſolida eſt; &amp; iam certiſſimè habetur, &amp; tamen de eius fiducia adhuc ſub dubitatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne trepidatur: Pars nam<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> eius prius acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitur ut in nobis poſtmodum perfectè com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleatur.</hi> Faith it ſelfe which ſeaſoneth vs to the receiuing of other graces, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly in the beginning thereof is both wavering and ſound; wee already moſt certeinely haue it, and yet of the aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance thereof we feare and doubt: For we firſt receiue a part of it, that it may bee af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:20803:21"/>perfectly fulfilled in vs.<note place="margin">Greg. Ibid. Faith and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beleefe, certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taintie, aſſura<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and doubt may be blended toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in one and the ſame man, why doth the Church of Rome now teach the contrary, ſaying that faith ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludeth all feare and doubt. The Scripture indeed commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding a feare vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, doth not meane a doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting feare, ſuch as is contrary to aſſurance of faith, but ſuch as is contrary to preſumption &amp; pride, and truſt in our ſelves, &amp; imparteth hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mlity, lowlines of mind, diſtruſt of our owne ſtrength, that we mày relie vpon the ſtrength and power of God. <hi>Mor. lib. 10. c. 8. Idem ibid.</hi>
                  </note> He bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth for example hereof, the poore man in the Goſpell to whom Chriſt ſaid, Marke 9. v. 23.24. <hi>If thou canſt beleeue, all things are poſſible to him that beleeueth.</hi> And he anſwered; <hi>Lord I beleeue, helpe my vnbeliefe. Vno eodemque tempore cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mabat ſe etiam credere &amp; adhuc ex incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulitate dubitare.</hi> At one and the ſame time (ſaith he) he cryed that hee did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, &amp; yet ſtill did doubt by vnbeliefe. <hi>Vno eodem<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pore is qui nec dum perfectè crediderat ſimul &amp; credebat, &amp; incredulus erat.</hi> At one and the ſame time (ſaith hee in another place) hee which did not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly beleeue, did both beleeue, and was alſo vnbeleeuing. And yet in another place he ſaith. <hi>Saepè conting it ut fides jam in mente vigeat, ſed tamen ex parte aliqua in dubietate contabeſcat. Vnam eandemque mentem &amp; certitudo ſolidae fidei roborat, &amp; tamen ex aliquantula mutabilitate perfidiae aura dubietatis verſat.</hi> It often falleth out, that faith now is growing in the minde, and yet by doubting it languiſheth in in ſome part; that certainery of ſound faith ſtrengthened one and the ſame
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:20803:22"/>mind, which notwithſtanding the winde of doubtfulneſſe ſhaketh by ſome muta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of vnbeliefe, as namely ſaith hee of the man before mentioned. <hi>Per fidem ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rans, &amp; per infidelitatem fluctuans dicebat, &amp;c. et exorare certus iam per fidem coepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat, &amp; adhuc incertus undas perfidiae ex in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credulitate tolerabat.</hi> Hoping by faith, and wavering by vnbeliefe, he ſaid, Lord I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, helpe my vnbeliefe.<note place="margin">He hoped in faith, yet wave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in vnbeliefe.</note> He beganne to pray (ſaith he) certaine now by faith and yet being vncertaine hee bare the waues of vnbeliefe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>§. 11.</hi> There is no Purgatory or third Place after this life.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>HOc de igne tribulationis in hac nobis vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta adhibito poteſt intelligi.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dial. 4. c. 39.</hi> Then it is no proofe for war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of a Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory after this life. <hi>Mor. ſuper Iob lib. 8. c. 8.</hi> If after death there be no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance, if there bee no change, but as the Angell ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther good or had receiveth the Soule out of the body, ſo it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinueth for euer, either exalted in ioy or drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: then there can bee no Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory, then there can be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but either heauen or hell, where they that come ſhall abide for ever. <hi>Lib. 7. indic. 2. epiſt. 111.</hi> Heere is no place for Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory, for heere he teacheth vs to beleeue, that the faithfull in death do attaine to true life, and that their paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage from this world is to a better, neither doth he acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge any vſe of Prayers, Maſſes, Trentals, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther offices and obſequies for the dead, who ſaith that our devotion and loue yeeldeth no fruit or profit to them.</note> The fire ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of in S. <hi>Paul.</hi> 1 Corinth. 3.13. may be vnderſtood of the fire of tribulation, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied vnto vs in this life.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quem nequaquam modò miſericordia e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ripit, ſola poſt praeſens ſeculum iuſticia ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicit, &amp;c.</hi> Whom Mercy now deliuereth not, him Iuſtice onely after this world
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:20803:22"/>impriſoneth. Heereof <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith, that in whatſoeuer place the tree falleth, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther toward the South, or towards the North, there it ſhalbe; becauſe at the time of a mans death, either the good Spirit, or the evill ſpirit, ſhall receiue the Soule go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from the Body, he ſhall hold it with him for euer, without any change, that neither being exalted, it can come downe to puniſhment; nor being drowned in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall puniſhments, can thence-forth riſe to any remedy of ſalvation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gregory</hi> writeth an Epiſtle to his friend <hi>Aregius</hi> a Biſhop, to comfort him, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in it is worthy to be obſerved, how con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly hee carrieth himſelfe to the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Scriptures. Amongſt other words we reade theſe, <hi>Indecens eſt de illis taedio afflictionis addici, quos credendum eſt ad veram vitam moriendo perveniſſe, &amp;c.</hi> It is vndecent for vs to giue our ſelues to long affliction of ſorrow for them, whom we are to beleeue to haue come by death vnto the true life. They haue haply iuſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe of long ſorrow, who know not any other life, who doe not beleeue the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage from this world, to bee to a better
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:20803:23"/>World, but we who know, who beleeue and teach this, are not to be too heavy for the dead, leſt that which with others car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieth a ſhew of piety, be to vs rather a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of blame. For it is in a maner a kind of diſtruſt to be tormented with heavineſſe, contrary to that which hee himſelfe doth teach. <hi>And then citing the words of Saint Paul,</hi> 1. Theſſ. 4.13. addeth. This therfore ſeeing we know, we are to haue a care, as I haue ſaid, not to bee afflicted for the dead, but to beſtow our affection vpon the living, to whom our piety or devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on may be profitable, and our loue may yeeld fruite.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="section">
               <head>§ <hi>12.</hi> No carrying about of the Reliques of the Saints.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>IN Romanis &amp; totius Occidentis partibus omninò intolerabile eſt atque ſacrilegum,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib. 3. epiſt. 30</hi> Is the doctrine of the Church of Rome, the ſame that it was of old? They now pull the Reliques fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the bodies of their imagined Saints and mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs: they vnbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry them out of their graues, kiſſe them, and carry them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, all which Gregory heere miſliketh.</note> 
                  <hi>ſi ſanctorum corpora tangere quiſquam for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſſe praeſumpſerit, certum eſt quia haec te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meritas impunita nullo modo remanebit.</hi> In the Romane Church, and the whole We<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterne parts, it was a thing altogether in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolerable,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:20803:23"/>and a matter of ſacriledge, to preſume to touch the bodies of the Saints; and if any man doe preſume ſo to do, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine it is, that his raſhneſſe ſhall by no meanes remaine vnpuniſhed. <hi>And then hauing ſhewed divers examples of them, who adventuring too neere to the ſtirring or touching the Bodies of ſome holy Perſons, were thereupon greatly frighted, or by death miſcaried, he concludeth,</hi> Who then know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing theſe things can be ſo raſh, as that he will preſume, I will not ſay, to touch the Bodies of ſuch, but in any ſort to looke vpon them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="section">
               <head>§. <hi>13.</hi> The Faith and Religion of the New Teſtament, differeth not in ſubſtance from the Old.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>In Evangel. hom. 19.</hi> The church be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Chriſt, was a part of that Church which hath beene called Catholike ſince Chriſts time If our faith be the ſame with the faith of the fathers of the old teſtament, then muſt it needs bee the Catholike faith. Idem in <hi>Ezec. hom. 15.</hi> The catholike Church is now vnderſtoode to containe all the faithful from the beginning of the world to the end. Of the catholike Church, there is but one body and one ſpirite which quickneth that body, and one faith wherby we are all partakers of that ſpirit. In pſal. paenit. <hi>5.</hi> Whether we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect them that were before the incarnation of Chriſt, or them that come after, they both make but one body, and therefore the holy Ghoſt as the Soule is but one and the ſame to both. <hi>In Ezech. hom. 16.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>HAbet vineam univerſalem ſcilicet Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiam, quae ab Abel iuſto, uſque ad ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timum electum, qui in fine mundi naſcitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus eſt quot ſanctos pertulit, quaſi tot palmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes miſit.</hi> God hath his Vineyard, even the Vniverſall Church, which yeeldeth ſo many branches as it bringerh forth Saints
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:20803:24"/>from righteous <hi>Abel,</hi> vnto the laſt Elect that ſhalbe borne in the end of the world.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vna eſt Eccleſia electorum praecedenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um at<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſequentium. Praetered omnes fideles qui ab</hi> Adam, <hi>in hunc uſque diem fuerunt, quive futuri ſunt quamdiu mundus dura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit, veram fidem profitentes ad candem Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiam pertinent.</hi> There is but one Church of the Elect, both before and ſince the time of Chriſt: moreover, all the Faithfull who haue beene from <hi>Adam</hi> till this day, and ſhall bee to the Worlds end, profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the true Faith, doe belong vnto the Catholike Church.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sicut eſt una anima quae diverſa corporis membra vivificat: ita totam ſimul Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am unus Spiritus Sanctus vegetat &amp; illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrat.</hi> As it is but one Soule which quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the divers members of the body, ſo one holy Spirit giveth life and light to the whole Church.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eadem fides, spes, charitas in antiquis patribus quae in novis doctoribus fuit.</hi> In the old Father was the faith, hope, and chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:20803:24"/>as in the new teachers, namely the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles and the reſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quod apud nos valet aqua baptiſmatis,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mor. l. 4. c. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>hoc egit apud veteres vel pro maioribus vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus ſacrificij, vel pro his qui ex Abrahae ſtirpe prodierant mysterium circumciſionis.</hi> Looke what the Water of Baptiſme avai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth with vs,<note place="margin">The Fathers of the Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment had the grace and effect of Baptiſme as well as we.</note> the ſame with the old Fathers did either faith onely for Infants, or for them of elder yeeres the power of ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, or for them that came of the ſtocke of <hi>Abraham,</hi> the Sacrament of Circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sive hi qui electi in Teſtamento Veteri fuerunt, ſive hi qui in Novo Teſtamento ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuti ſunt, nimirum conſtat,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In Ezech. hom. 16.</note> 
                  <hi>quia omnes ex amore Trinitatis accenſi ſunt, &amp;c. Ad ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram ſpeciem ex Trinitatis ſunt cognitione decorati.</hi> Whether we reſpect or reckon the Elect in the Old Teſtament,<note place="margin">The Fathers of the Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of Godhead, did ſee diſtinctly three Perſons, the Father, the Sonne, and the holy Ghoſt. <hi>In Cant. cap. 5.</hi>
                  </note> or they that followed in the New, they were all enkindled with the loue, and adorned vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to true beauty, through the knowledge of the holy Trinity.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Apoſtoli à Prophetarum dictis vt fortes perſiſterent, fidem integram acceperunt.</hi> The Apoſtles received the whole faith, to
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:20803:25"/>the end they might ſtand firme,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>In Ezech. hom. 6.</hi> The law &amp; the prophets and the Goſpells and the preaching of the Apoſtles, haue all deliuered only one and the ſame thing. <hi>Ibid.</hi> Chriſt confirmed the ſame faith and religion, which the Iew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh Church be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore receiued, &amp; added nothing touching the ſubſtance of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine. The Apoſtles in preaching the Goſpell ſaid no other things but thoſe which the prophets and Moſes did ſay ſhould come.</note> from thoſe things, that were ſpoken by the Prophets. And again. <hi>Quod praedicat Lex, hoc etiam Prophetae; quod denuntiant Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetae, hoc exhibet Evangelinin; quod exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buit Evangelium, hoc praedicaverunt Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoli per mundum.</hi> Looke what the Law preacheth, the ſame alſo doe the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets teach, the ſame the Goſpell hath exhibited, and what the Goſpell exhibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited, the Apoſtles preached through the world.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vira<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> teſtamenta in nullo à ſe diſcrepa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp;c. Ineſt teſtamento veteri, teſtamentum novum &amp;c. Prophetia teſtamenti novi, te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtamentum vetus eſt, &amp; expoſitio teſtamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti veteris, teſtamentum novum.</hi> The two Teſtaments differ not in any thing one from the other, the new Teſtament is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the old. The old Teſtament is a prophecie of the new, and the new Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the expoſition of the old.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="section">
               <head>§, <hi>14.</hi> What was ſaid to Peter Mat. <hi>16.</hi> whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver thou bindeſt &amp;c. was spoken to the whole Church.</head>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:20803:25"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>VNiverſali Eccleſiae dicitur,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>In 1. Reg. lib. 6 cap. 3.</hi> The Pope is an vſurper againſt God and the Church.</note> 
                  <hi>Quod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ligaveris, &amp;c.</hi> It was ſaid to the Vniverſall Church, Whatſoeuer thou bindeſt in earth, ſhall be bound in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="section">
               <head>§. <hi>15.</hi> How farre God ſuffereth Sin, and guideth the wicked actions of wicked men.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>OMnipotens Deus quod fieri prohibet,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mor. l. 11. c. 2. &amp; lib. 16. c. 23.</hi> There is much good wrought out of evill, which could not be without evil. Hereupon the malicious Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts ſay, that we make God the author of ſin. <hi>Ibid. lib. 6. c. 12</hi> To God we at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute no more but that he vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntarily per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitteth, &amp; wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ordereth, and iuſtly vſeth to his purpoſes the ſin of man: and ſo much their owne Pope Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory ſaith. Conſider the act of ſin in it ſelfe, it is properly and only the worke of man: but if we conſider it in the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, it is rightly called the worke of God. <hi>Moral. lib. 18. cap. 17. Mor. lib. 2. c. 6.</hi> It was the Spirit of the Lord, that vexed Saul. <hi>Ibid. l. 18. c. 3. Ibid. l. 2. cap. 6.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>iuſt um eſt ut fieri ſinat. Inulium abire non ſinit iniuſtum, quod iustè fieri permiſit.</hi> It is iuſt, that the Almighty God ſuffer that to be done, which notwithſtanding he forbiddeth to be done, neither ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth he that vniuſtice to go vnrevenged, which he iuſtly ſuffered to be done.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Miro modo fit, ut quod ſine volu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tate Dei agitur eius voluntati contrarium non ſit, quia du<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in bonu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> uſum malafacta vertu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tur, eius conſilio militant, etiam quae eius conſilio repugnant.</hi> It commeth ſtrangely to paſſe, that that which is done without the will of God, yet is not againſt his wil, becauſe whileſt evill deedes are turned to good
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:20803:26"/>vſe, thoſe things ſhew the Counſell and Will of God, which notwithſtanding are repugnant vnto it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ab iniquis facta ne inordinatè eveniant ipſe disponens.</hi> God diſpoſeth the doings of wicked men, that they may not befall vnorderly.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nus idem<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Spiritus &amp; Domini appel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latur &amp; malus; Domini per licentiam po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testatis iuſtae, malus per deſiderium volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis iniuſtae.</hi> It was the ſpirit of the Lord (that vexed <hi>Saul</hi>) by leaue and licence of iuſt power; but an evill ſpirit by deſire of vniuſt will.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Omnis Diaboli</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">For poteſtas, reade volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas.</note> 
                  <hi>potestas</hi> * <hi>iniuſta eſt, &amp; tamen permittente Deo, omnis poteſtas iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta.</hi> The will of the divell is altogether vniuſt, but his power which of Gods per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion only he hath, is altogether iuſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Deo ad uſum iuſti indicij &amp; iniuſta Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boli voluntas ſervit.</hi> The vniuſt will of the divell ſerveth GOD for the vſe of iuſt iudgment.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Inde coacti ſunt Dei voluntatem pera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gere,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Moral. lib. 6. c. 22.</hi> Albeit God by his wiſedome &amp; power doe turne the evill of wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked men to his good purpoſe &amp; vſe; yet they do it not as with any purpoſe therein to ſerve God, but to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the ſinfull luſts of their owne wicked hearts, &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore are iuſtly puniſhed for the doing of it. As is ſeene mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly in theſe examples. Wickednes iſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth wholly out of mans heart: but God by his ſecret hand guideth it to go one way rather then an other.</note> 
                  <hi>unde hanc moliti ſunt aſtutè commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tare. Cum ſe aestimant cius miracula per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequendo abſcindere haec nimirum compulſi
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:20803:26"/>ſunt neſciendo dilatare. Hoc ad pietatis ſuae obſequium redigit, quod contra illum hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mana crudelitas exarſit. Cüi cognitae debet noſtra actio devotè famulari, ne ei etiam no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cens ſerviat, ſi hanc ſuperbiens declinat.</hi> Thereby <hi>Ioſephs</hi> brethren were compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to doe the will of God, whereby they ſubtilly thought to defeate the ſame. The Iewes by perſecuting, thought to cut off the miracles of Chriſt, but were compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vnwittingly to ſpread the ſame fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. God forceth that to the ſervice of his piety, wherein humane cruelty burneth or rageth againſt him. Our acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on even againſt our will ſerveth the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly will of God, when in our pride it ſhunneth the ſame.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="section">
               <head>§. <hi>16.</hi> The auncient Church knew not the idolatry uſed now in the Church of Rome, in worſhipping of Images.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>INdico dudum ad nos perveniſſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lib. 7. Ep. 109.</note> 
                  <hi>quod fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternitas veſtra quoſdam imaginum ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratores
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:20803:27"/>aſpiciens eaſdem Eccleſiae imagines confregit at<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> proiecit. Et quide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> zelu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vos ne quid manu factum adorari poſſit habuiſſe laudavimus, ſed frangere eaſdem imagines non debuiſſe iudicamus, &amp;c.</hi> I certifie you (ſaith <hi>Gregory,</hi> to <hi>Serenus</hi> Biſhop of Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilia) that it came of late to our hearing, that your Brother-hood beholding ſome worſhipping Images, did break the ſame Church-images, and threw them away. And ſurely, I commended you that you had that zeale, that nothing made with hands ſhould bee worſhipped. But yet I iudge, that you ſhould not haue broken thoſe images. For therefore is the picture vſed in the Church, that they who are not learned by Booke, may yet by ſight reade vpon the walles, thoſe things which they cannot reade in Bookes. Therefore your Brother-hood ſhould both preſerue the images, and forbid the people the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping of them, that both the ignorant may haue whence to gather the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Hiſtory, and the people may not ſinne in worſhipping of the Picture. <hi>Convocandi ſunt disperſi Eccleſiae filij eis<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Scripturae Sacrae eſt teſtimonijs oſtendendis,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Idem. l. 9. ep. 9.</note>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:20803:27"/>
                  <hi>quia omne manufactum adorare non liceat, quoniam ſcriptum eſt, Dominum Deum tuu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> adorabis, &amp; illi ſoli ſervies.</hi> The Children of the Church are againe to bee gathered together, and it muſt be ſhowen by teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of the Scriptures, that it is not lawful to worſhip any thing that is made with hands, becauſe it is written. Thou ſhalt worſhip the Lord thy God, &amp; him onely thou ſhalt ſerue.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Frangi non debuit quod non adorandum in Eccleſijs,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Greg. ibid.</note> 
                  <hi>ſed ad inſtruendas ſolummodo mentes fuit neſcientium collocatum.</hi> That ought not to be broken, which was not ſet vp in the Church to be adored, <hi>but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to inſtruct the ignorant.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Scio quidem quod Imaginem Salvatoris noſtri non ideo petis ut quaſi Deum colas,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib. 7. epiſt. 54</hi> Heere we ſee that Gregory doth not inſtruct Secundinus, as the Papiſts now adayes doe their Schollers. As to worſhip the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, or to kneel to it, for that he condemneth; But willeth him to vnderſtand that theſe deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions belong only to God, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that he muſt beware not to put the image in the place of God to doe to it thoſe duties of religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons humiliation which are proper to God alone. <hi>Ibid. lib. 9. e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt. 9.</hi> Not to worſhip images, but to haue them for remembrance, not to fall downe before them but to worſhip chriſt whome we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> 
                  <hi>ſed ob recordationem filij Dei, ut in eius a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more recaleſcas, cuius te Imaginem videre conſideras, &amp;c.</hi> I know verily (ſaith <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory</hi> to <hi>Secundinus</hi>) that thou doeſt not therefore deſire the Image of our Saviour that thou mayſt worſhip it as God, but for a remembrance of the Sonne of God, that thou mayſt become fervent in his loue, whoſe Image thou conſidereſt thy
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:20803:28"/>ſelfe to behold. And wee verily fall not downe before it, as before the Godhead, but we worſhip him whom by the Image we remember, either as borne, or hauing ſuffered, or now ſitting vpon his Throne; and whileſt the Picture, as it were a wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, bringeth to our remembrance the Sonne of GOD, either it reioyceth our mind as touching his reſurrection, or ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſeth it by his paſſion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Si quis imagines facere voluerit minime prohibe: adorare verò imagines omnibus modis devita; ſed hoc ſolicite fraternitas tua admoneat, ut ex viſione rei goſta ardore<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> compunctionis percipiant, &amp; in adoratione ſolius omnipotentis ſanctae Trinitatis humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liter proſternantur.</hi> If any man will make images, forbid him not: but by al meanes avoide the worſhipping of Images: But this let your Brother-hood carefully ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertiſe them, by the ſight of the ſtory, to gather fervency of compunction, but humbly to fall downe or kneele in the worſhip of the holy Trinity onely.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="section">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:20803:28"/>
               <head>§. <hi>17.</hi> The Bookes of the Machabees are not Canonicall Scripture; of the eaſines of the Scriptures, and fulnes without traditions.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>NOn inordinatè agimus, ſi ex libris,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mor. lib. 19. c. 16. aut. 13.</hi> The church of Rome now doth accurſe all thoſe that refuſe the bookes of the Machabees (of which Gregorie heere ſpeaketh) for canonicall Scripture. <hi>In Ezech. l. 1. hom. 9. ad fine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> The church of Rome now ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſeth all thoſe that doe not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons vnwritten, as they doe the written word. <hi>Mor. l. 18. c. 14. in princ.</hi> The Papiſts are theſe heretickes: from the writté word, they fly to traditions vnto them. <hi>Lib. 4. epiſt. 40 ad Theod. Medicum.</hi> Gregory ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horteth Lay men to the reading of the Scriptures. The Papiſts for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid them.</note> 
                  <hi>licet non Canonicis, ſed tamen ad aedificatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem Eccleſiae editis teſtimonia proferamus.</hi> We doe not deale diſorderly, if we doe bring forth teſtimonies out of bookes that are <hi>not canonicall;</hi> yet are publiſhed for the aedification of the Church.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In hoc volumine, omnia quae erudiunt, cuncta quae aedificant ſcripta continentur; libri ſacri ad loquendum nobis quaſi quaeda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> argenti venae ſunt.</hi> In this volume are all things which doe inſtruct, and which doe edifie conteined. The holy Bookes are vnto vs to ſhew vs how to ſpeake, as cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine veines of ſiluer, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Saepè haeretici dum ſua ſtudent perverſa aſtruere, ea proferunt quae in ſacrorum li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brorum paginis non tenentur.</hi> Hererikes doe vſually for the confirmation of their
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:20803:29"/>perverſe opinions ſuggeſt ſuch proofes as are not found in the Scriptures.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sicuti terreni Imperatoris ſcripta acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peres, non quieſceres, nec ſomnum oculis da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res priuſquam ſcripta illa agnoviſſes; Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perator coeli, Augelorum ac hominum Deus tibi pro vita tua epiſtolas ſuas tranſmiſit, &amp; tamen eas ardenter legere negligis: Stude ergo quaeſo, &amp; Creatoris tui verba medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, diſce cor Dei in verbis Dei.</hi> And a little before, <hi>Quid eſt autem Scriptura Sacra, ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi Epiſtola omnipotentis Dei ad creatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram ſuam?</hi> Whereſoeuer thou receiueſt the Letters of an earthly Prince, thou do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt not reſt, nor giue ſleepe to thine eyes, before thou doeſt vnderſtand thoſe Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. The Emperour of Heauen, and God of Angels and men, ſendeth his Writings vnto thee for direction of thy life: &amp; yet thou doeſt neglect to reade them earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Study therefore, I pray thee, and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate on the words of thy Creator. Learn the mind of God in the word of God; for what is the holy Scripture, but an Epiſtle of the Omnipote<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t God vnto his Creature.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Magnae vtilitatis eſt ipſa obſcuritas e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquiorum Dei,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lib. <hi>1.</hi> hom. <hi>6.</hi> ſuper Ezech.</note> 
                  <hi>quia exercet ſenſum—vt
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:20803:29"/>exercitatus capiat quod capere nequit, oci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oſus habeat quo<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> adhuc maius aliud; quia ſi in cunctis ſacrae ſcripturae intelligentia eſſet aperta, vileſceret, quae in quibuſdam locis obſcurioribus in venta animum reficit.</hi> The very obſcuritie of the Scriptures of God, is of great profit and commoditie,<note place="margin">To oppoſe the obſcuritie of the Scriptures to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terre men from the reading of them is a very frothy argument and condemned by Gregory.</note> becauſe it exerciſeth the vnderſtanding, that he that is exerciſed in them may vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand that which he could not; he that is idle may haue alſo ſome more occaſion to ſearch them becauſe if the meaning of the holy ſcripture were plain in al things, it would be of no account, which being found out in certain obſcure places, doth refreſh the minde.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Scriptura quaſi quidam fluvius eſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Epiſt. ad Leand. cap. <hi>4.</hi> ſup. mor.</note> 
                  <hi>vt dixerim planus &amp; altus in quo &amp; agnus ambulet &amp; Elephas natet.</hi> The Scripture is as it were a certaine river as I haue ſaid ſhallow and deepe; wherein the lambe may goe or walke, and the Elepha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſwim.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>§. 18.</hi> The Catholike Church in the Creed, is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued, not ſeene: and conſiſteth of all the elect only, and excludeth the reprobate out of it.</head>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:20803:30"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>IN carne Dominus ad Eccleſiam veniens —fines Eccleſiae occulti iudicij diſtinxit.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mor. l. <hi>28.</hi> cap. <hi>6</hi> The diſtinction of viſible &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible Church, muſt not be take away. Gregory denieth that wicked me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and ſuch as are the limbs of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than, may bee truely members of the body of Christ, or that they belong to the Catholique Church. The Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts affirm they may. In. Pſ. <hi>5. poenit. poſt principiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; in principio</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Intra has menſuras ſunt omnes electi, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra has ſunt omnes reprobi, etiamſi intra fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dei limitem eſſe videantur.</hi> Our Lord com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming in the fleſh vnto the Church, ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated the bounds thereof, by the inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his hidden iudgement, <hi>within whoſe limits are all the elect,</hi> and without thoſe limits are all the reprobate, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they ſeeme to bee within the bond of faith.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sanctam Eccleſiam de ſanctis in aeternu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> permanſuris conſtructam, nullis huius vita perſecutionibus ſuperandam, ipſe ſuper qui aedificate eſt evidenter oſtendit, cum ait, Portae inferi non praevalebunt adverſus ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Vnum corpus est tota ſancta vniverſalis ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſia ſub Christo Ieſu capite ſuo conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta. &amp;c.</hi> He vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whom the Church is buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded doth evidently ſhew,<note place="margin">The glorious ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles of Spowſe &amp; Catholike Church, doe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly belong and appertaine vnto the faithfull and elect of God. The Church of Rome now ſaith that the Catholike Church is viſible and palpable, as is the kingdome of great Brittain and of France. And that one &amp; the ſame man may be a mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Chriſt, in reſpect of out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward profeſſion; and a member of the divell, in respect of his wicked life. Hor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rible doctrine &amp; moſt contrary to that taught here by S. Gregory. For tell me Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt, what ſociety is there between Chriſt and Beli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, that both they ſhould ſhare in one Man. In Iob. l. <hi>18.</hi> c. <hi>27</hi> &amp; l. <hi>12.</hi> c. <hi>5. in principio.</hi> Gregory excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth none from being conceaued in ſinne but our Saviour Chriſt; The Papiſts ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the Virgin Mary.</note> that the holy Church which is gathered together of Saints who ſhall continue for ever, &amp; not be overcome with any the perſecutions of this life, when he ſaith, <hi>The gates of hell ſhal not prevaile againſt it.</hi> The whole ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vniverſall Church is one body, eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:20803:30"/>vnder one head Ieſus Chriſt. Chriſt therefore with his whole Church whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that which is converſant at this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent in earth; or that which raigneth with him in heauen, is one perſon; and as there is one ſoule which quickneth divers me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the body, ſo one holy ſpirit doth at once quicken and illuſtrate the whole Church. For as Chriſt who is head of the Church was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceiued by the holy Ghoſt; ſo the holy Church which is his body is filled with the ſame ſpirite to life euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting; wherby the whol body vnderprop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped and framed, doth grow to an increaſe in God. That is the body out of which the ſpirite doth not quicken.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>§. 19.</hi> Only Chriſt was conceiued by the holy ghoſt without any touch of ſinne.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>ILle ſolus veraciter ſanctus natus eſt, qui vt ipſam conditionem naturae vinceret, ex commixtione carnalis copulae concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus non est. nullus homo ſine peccato est, niſi ille qui in hunc mundum non venit ex pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cato.</hi> He only indeed was borne holy, who
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:20803:31"/>that hee might overcome that condition of nature was not conceaued by the mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of carnall copulation. No man is without ſinne, but he who came into this world through ſinne.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>§. 20.</hi> The Pope vſurpeth the title of vniverſall Biſhop, which Gregory refuſed.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>EGo fidenter dico, quiſquis ſe vniverſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Sacerdotem vocat,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lib. <hi>40.</hi> epiſt. <hi>30.</hi> He that claim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the title of the Vniverſall Biſhop, is the forerunner of Antechriſt, but the Papiſts giue that title to the Pope. <hi>Ergo.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>vel vocari deſiderat in elatione ſua Antichriſtum praecurrit; quia ſuperbiendo ſe caeteris praeponit.</hi> I ſpeak it boldly, whoſoever calleth himſelfe <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſall Biſhop,</hi> or deſireth ſo to bee cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, is in his pride the forerunner of <hi>Ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt,</hi> becauſe in making himſelf proud, <hi>he ſetteth himſelfe before other.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hac in re à fratre &amp; conſacerdote me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> contra Evangelicam ſententiam &amp;c.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 4. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 34.</note> Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in my Brother and fellow Biſhop doth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the meaning of the Goſpel, againſt S. <hi>Peter</hi> the Apoſtle, againſt all Churches, and againſt the ordinance of the Canons. In this pride of his, what other thing is there betokned, but the time of Ante-Chriſt
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:20803:31"/>is even at hand? For hee foloweth him, that deſpiſing the equalitie of ioy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Angells, laboured to breake vp to the top of <hi>ſingularitie,</hi> ſaying thus,<note place="margin">The Pope in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe aboue all other Biſhops, imitateth Luci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer in his ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laritie, ſetting himſelfe aboue the reſt of the Angells. Lib. <hi>4.</hi> Epiſt. <hi>38.</hi>
                  </note> I will advance my throne aboue the ſtarres of heauen, I will ſit in the mount of the Teſtament even in the corners of the North; I will get me vp aboue the light of the cloudes, and will bee like vnto the higheſt. <hi>Rex ſuperbiae in foribus eſt</hi> &amp;c. The king of pride is even in the gates; and an horrible thing to ſpeake <hi>Sacordotum eſt paratus exercitus,</hi> an army of Prieſts is made ready, for now they play the ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and beare their heads of high that were ordained to be captaines of humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nether may you ſay,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 6. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 28.</note> that the vſing of this title is nothing; for if wee beare this matter quietly, we overthrowe the faith of the whole Church. The agreeing vnto this wicked title is the loſing of the faith.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nullus Romanorum pontificum hoc ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularitatis nomen aſſumpſit.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 4. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 32.</note> None of the Biſhops of Rome ever receiued this name of ſingularitie: <hi>nullus deceſſorum meorum hoc tam profano vocabulo vti voluit:</hi> None
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:20803:32"/>of my predeceſſors ever conſented to vſe this vngodly name. <hi>Nos hunc honorem nolumus oblatum ſuſcipere.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 4. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 36.</note> We being Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops of Rome will not take this honour being offered vnto vs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quid tu Chriſto vniverſalis Eccleſiae ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piti, in extremi iudicij dicturus es examini qui cuncta eius membra tibimet conaris v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niver ſalis appellatione ſupponere?</hi> What anſwere wilt thou make vnto Chriſt, that indeed is the head of the vniverſal church at the triall of the laſt iudgement, that thou goeſt about vnder the name of <hi>Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall Biſhop, to ſubdue all his members vnto thee?</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>An elucidation touching this title, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſall Biſhop.</head>
                  <p>The occaſion of theſe speeches of Gregory againſt this title of <hi>Vniverſall Biſhop,</hi> was the pride of Iohn, who was Patriarch of the Church of Constantinople, who did indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vor to draw that title vnto himſelfe, againſt which Gregory as you ſee excepteth, and would not that either Iohn, or any other ſhould vſurpe that name. And as Gregory
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:20803:32"/>withſtood it then, ſo doe we now; &amp; ſet him againſt the Church of Rome, as oppoſite to it. The Papiſts finding Gregories teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies true, doe yet put a difference (in ſecreat meaning) betweene the power and authority which Iohn intended by it for himſelfe, and that which they intend by it for the Pope: which is this. Iohn (ſay they) by ſtriuing for that title attributed it ſo vnto himſelfe, that he meant to be called Biſhop alone, ſo as Biſhopricke ſhould bee taken away from all other; and to be ſuch an one as is a Biſhop alone and altogether and only, ſo as there be no other Biſhop beſides him: finally, that Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop Vniverſall by Gregory, is as much as al Biſhops; whereas we giuing it to the Pope, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barre not others from being Biſhops, or the Church from hauing ſuch, but make him V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſall Biſhop, over and aboue all other, as being the higheſt of all, and hauing power over all other Biſhops. Therefore the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of Gregory is in this caſe very imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly alleaged againſt the Pope, who doth not take it in that nature wherein Iohn would haue vſurped it, but rightly vſeth it, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Gregories meaning. Thus ſay they; but here is a bare, a naked, and an idle ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culation
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:20803:33"/>of their owne braine. For it ſhal ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare notwithſtanding this fond illation of theirs from the very text and tenor of Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gories wordes by the precedent authorities, and ſome more of his conſequent, that Iohn never meant, nor Gregory never ſo did vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand him, as that he would be vniverſal Biſhop, thereby to take away all other, but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven as the Biſhop of Rome now doth, thereby to bring the reſt in ſubiection vnto him. Which if it be ſo, then is not the autohrity anſwered, but they condemned by the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict of their great S. Gregory, who is in time from vs more then <hi>1000</hi> yeares.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>To proue this let vs record the firſt teſtimony againe.</head>
                  <p>He that claimeth that title (ſaith <hi>Gregory)</hi> is the forerunne of Antechriſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in making himſelfe prowd, <hi>hee ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth himſelfe before other.</hi> Loe! A plaine text, againſt their forged gloſſe. <hi>Gregory</hi> doth not ſay,<note place="margin">How can he bee before other that hath no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther but him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</note> 
                     <hi>hee would haue no other but himſelfe: But that he ſetteth himſelfe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore other. Before other.</hi> marke that.</p>
                  <p>In the ſecond. He is like to him in the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:20803:33"/>ſingularity of his pride, that deſpiſed the <hi>equalitie</hi> of ioy among Angels, ſaying. I will advance my throne aboue the ſtars of heauen, &amp;c. Here is ſeene the ſingulari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of one, that would be aboue many; but nothing of one, that would haue none beſides himſelfe.</p>
                  <p>In the laſt there, it is ſaid.<note place="margin">Vlt.</note> Though goeſt about to ſubdue all the members of Chriſt vnto thee. To <hi>ſubdue them; but not to take them cleane away.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Writing to Mauritius the Emperour a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout this matter, he ſaith,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Lib.</hi> 4. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 32.</note> 
                     <hi>Vtinam vel ſine aliorum (non ſublatione ſed) imminutione vnus ſit, qui vocari appetit vniverſalis.</hi> I would to God he might be one, without the <hi>leſſning</hi> of others, who deſireth to bee called <hi>vniverſall.</hi> Without the leſſning of others (ſaith he) not without vtter taking away of others.</p>
                  <p>To the Empreſſe <hi>Conſtantia</hi> thus.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Lib.</hi> 4. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 34.</note> 
                     <hi>Illud appetere Iohannem vt omnibus dignior eſſe videatur.</hi> Iohn deſireth that hee might ſeeme worthier than all other. Not but that there ſhould be others as well as he: But that hee might ſeeme worthier than other.</p>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:20803:34"/>
                  <p>To <hi>Elogius</hi> Biſhop of Alexandria <hi>Per elationem pompatici ſermonis, Chriſti ſibi ſtudet membra ſubiugare.</hi> By the hautines of a <hi>glorious title</hi> hee ſtudieth to bring in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſubiection vnto him the members of Chriſt. To bring them vnder ſubiection (ſaith he) not to cut of any.</p>
                  <p>To <hi>Iohn</hi> himſelfe thus. <hi>Appetere eum vocabulum hoc,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Lib.</hi> 4. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 18.</note> 
                     <hi>vt nulli ſubeſſe, &amp; ſolus omnibus praeſſe videretur.</hi> That he did af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect that title, that he might be ſubiect to none, and ſeeme only to be over all. So, it appeareth here alſo, that he would not be Biſhop alone; but ſubiect to none, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all. Moreover hee faith vnto him <hi>Quid dicturus es,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ibid.</note> 
                     <hi>qui non ſolum Pater ſed Generalis Pater in mundo vocari appetis?</hi> What wilt thou ſay who doſt not deſire to be called only father in the world, but vniverſall or generall father? Generall fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (ſaith he) not father alone. And that which in this qeſtion taketh away all ſcruple (he ſaith) <hi>Cupere Iohannem Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cops ſemetipſum vocabulo elationis praepo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere, eoſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ſub ſe premere.</hi> That <hi>Iohn</hi> doth deſire by this title of pride to ſet himſelfe before all other Biſhops, and to tread the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <pb n="45" facs="tcp:20803:34"/>vnder him. But ſet himſelfe before others or bring others vnder him, he could not, vnleſſe there bee ſome, whom he may bring vnder, &amp; before who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he may exalt himſelfe. Iohn there would be chiefe, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toll himſelfe, be greater than the reſt, bee called generall father: But he would not expell the reſt of the Biſhops, but bring them vnder him, ſubiect them to him; di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſh their authoritie, and bring them to naught.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>A ſecond elucidation or cleering of the ſame Queſtion.</head>
                  <p>When <hi>Iohn</hi> died <hi>Cyriacus</hi> ſucceded. <hi>Iohn</hi> ſate there tenne whole yeares. <hi>Iohn</hi> had ſitten there tenne whole yeares, hee claymed the title of <hi>Vniuerſall</hi> to his death, nor weighed hee the admonitions of <hi>Gregory,</hi> yet carried hee himſelfe for thoſe tenne yeares for <hi>Vniuerſall,</hi> yet in al that time, did not hee diſcharge any Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of his place. Wherefore it is a meere fable, to thinke there ſhould be no Biſhop or Patriarch if there were any called <hi>Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uverſall. Cyriacus</hi> as in ſeat, ſo in title ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:20803:35"/>
                     <hi>Iohn,</hi> He tooke away no Biſhops. He called a Councel of Biſhops, to which when <hi>Euſebius</hi> came, <hi>Gregory</hi> deſired of him by his letter, that he would not ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe to that title, leaſt any thing ſhould be there determined preiudiciall touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge any place or perſon. But neither in that <hi>ſynode,</hi> nor for eleuen yeers after, while <hi>Cyriacus</hi> held the ſea (&amp; that with the title of <hi>Vniuerſall)</hi> was there any Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop remoued from his place, or any feare that any ſhould be remoued. Therfore that deviſe before is a meere dream. Tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching <hi>Cyriacus</hi> this is certaine, that hee never left off the title of <hi>Vniuerſall,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that <hi>Phocas</hi> the Emperour tooke it from Conſtantinople, and gaue it vnto Rome. And this was done by <hi>Phocas</hi> in malice towards <hi>Cyriacus</hi> who was offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with him, and in favour of <hi>Boniface</hi> 3. Biſhop of Rome who intreated for it,<note place="margin">Boniface was Biſhop of Rome next but one after Gregory.</note> and when he was the Biſhops Chancelour in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuated himſelfe into <hi>Phocas</hi> his loue, &amp; had vndertaken for his child at baptiſme. This decree of <hi>Phocas,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ad annum <hi>606</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Baronius</hi> doth thus report, <hi>The Biſhop of Rome is only to bee called Vniverſall Biſhop, the Biſhop of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:20803:35"/>not ſo.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Iohn</hi> and <hi>Cyriacus</hi> therefore uſurped nothing, but that which vpon the grant of <hi>Phocas,</hi> the Romane Biſhop doth now claime, vnder whom they remain in their place, and are Biſhops; And ſo vnder <hi>Iohn</hi> did they remaine, neither did the title of <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſall</hi> hinder them any thing. Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, within a little while after there is a great change made <hi>touching the name.</hi> In the Biſhop of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> it was <hi>a fooliſh, prowd, wicked, perverſe, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane, and blaspheamous name;</hi> within two yeares after, it was none of all thoſe in the Biſhop of Rome. Marveilous was the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of <hi>Phocas,</hi> who determined that a name <hi>wicked</hi> and <hi>blaſphemous</hi> (if wee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue <hi>Gregory)</hi> ſhould not belong to the Biſhop of Conſtantinople, and yet might be <hi>proper</hi> to the Biſhop of Ro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e. Wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full alſo was the intent of <hi>Boniface,</hi> who accepted it; neither would he that the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Conſtantinople ſhould bee pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred, or be aboue others, but to him &amp; other the Biſhops of Rome ſuch reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence is due, although he that ſhal haue it (witneſſe <hi>Gregory)</hi> ſhould bee in that the
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:20803:36"/>
                     <hi>follower of Lucifer,</hi> the <hi>forerunner of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techriſt.</hi> In the meane while <hi>Gregory</hi> was a true <hi>Prophet,</hi> touching what that word would come too in the end. For touching that title hee told the Emperour that <hi>hee that ſhould reioyce in it,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Lib.</hi> 4. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 32.</note> 
                     <hi>would build him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe by that vpon the honour of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire,</hi> and is it not come ſo to paſſe? And to <hi>Anianus</hi> he ſaid. That to conſent to that wicked name, is no other thing then to deſtroy the faith. And did the <hi>faith</hi> ſuffer no hurt, by that that <hi>Phocas</hi> conſented to it? <hi>Gregories</hi> prophecie was true in both, that name was deadly, both to the <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire</hi> and to the <hi>Church;</hi> and his ſucceſſour <hi>Boniface,</hi> was toward the Empire <hi>Luci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer,</hi> and toward the Church <hi>Antechrist.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But they inſiſt,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Lib.</hi> 4. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 38. Reſtat vt vos Epiſcopi non ſitis. Solus conetur Epiſcopus ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellari.</note> and reply, the words are plaine. <hi>It remaineth that then you are no Biſhops: hee onely indeavoreth to bee called Biſhop.</hi> Therefore <hi>Gregory</hi> doth expound himſelfe. We reioine, thus hee writeth to <hi>Iohn. Cupis Epiſcoporum nomen, tui com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratione calcare.</hi> Thou doſt deſire in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of thy ſelfe, to tread vnder the name of Biſhops. In compariſon of thy ſelfe, ſaith he. Therefore what he ſaith, he
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:20803:36"/>ſaith it <hi>comparatiuely,</hi> or by way of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon, not <hi>abſolutely.</hi> Yee are indeed <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops,</hi> but in compariſon of him, yee are none; and he is not <hi>abſolutely</hi> a Biſhop <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone,</hi> but in compariſon of you, he only is to be called a <hi>Biſhop.</hi> For when the <hi>title of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſall is admitted,</hi> whereby one may be aboue another, and depreſſe the reſt; they fall from the ancient right of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, by which right they are of <hi>one me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit</hi> and <hi>prieſthood.</hi> Neither doth the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tency of <hi>Rome</hi> make an higher <hi>Biſhop,</hi> nor the poverty of <hi>Eugubium</hi> make a low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. All are to bee depriued of this due ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, if any thing <hi>private</hi> be giuen to one (as <hi>Gregory</hi> ſaith to <hi>Mauritius</hi>) &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſurely <hi>in compariſon of him,</hi> (which they were before) are not to be called Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops: ſpeaking after the vſuall phraſe, wherein, when <hi>any one is not, that he was, he is ſaid indeed not to be at all;</hi> ſo that hee <hi>may be ſaid to bee alone,</hi> who in any thing <hi>is ſingular.</hi> For they who were <hi>Fathers,</hi> were to be made the <hi>Sonnes</hi> of this <hi>Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall father;</hi> They who were <hi>Paſtors,</hi> were to come into his flocke; &amp; in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of him, to be called a <hi>flocke.</hi> And
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:20803:37"/>this is the nature of <hi>Gregories</hi> words; he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they reach. Againſt this they cannot be drawne; excep againſt the truth of the hiſtories, by which it is certaine, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though for the ſpace of <hi>twentie yeares Iohn</hi> firſt,<note place="margin">This is the hinge where vpon all the whole worke doth turne.</note> and <hi>Cyriacus</hi> after, held the title of <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſall</hi> with tooth and naile: yet in all that time they never indeavored to ſtrip any of his Biſhopricke, or ſo to carry themſelues as though they alone would be <hi>Biſhops,</hi> or vſurped the name of Biſhop only to themſelues.</p>
                  <p>Theſe things being thus, and thus co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered; that which was ſaid at firſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth full and ſound; That the <hi>Pope</hi> v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurpeth the <hi>title</hi> of <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſall Biſhop.</hi> That <hi>Gregory</hi> condemned it in <hi>Iohn.</hi> And laſtly that <hi>Iohns</hi> intent then, &amp; the <hi>Popes</hi> now touching that <hi>title,</hi> is one and the ſame, to all conſtructions and purpoſes; any thing, in any wiſe ſaid to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry notwithſtanding.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>§ 21.</hi> The Biſhop of Rome acknowledged the Emperour to be his Lord and Soveraigne.</head>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:20803:37"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>ECce per me ſervum ultimum ſuum,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lib 3. epiſt. 61 ad Mauritium Imperatore<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp; veſtrum reſpondebit Chriſtus ſacerdotes meos manui tuae commiſi, &amp;c. Ego quidem veſtrae iuſſioni ſubiectus, legem veſtram per diverſas terrarum partes tranſmitti feci.</hi> Behold (ſaith <hi>Gregory</hi> to <hi>Mauritius</hi> the Emperor) thus will Chriſt anſwere you by mee, beeing both his and your moſt humble ſervant;<note place="margin">Gregory acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour to bee his Lord and Souc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne.</note> I haue committed my Prieſts into thy hand, &amp;c. As for my part, I being ſubiect to your Maieſties com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, haue cauſed your order to bee proclaimed thorough divers parts of the world.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chriſtus dominari Imperatorem, non ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum militibus, ſed etiam Sacerdotibus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſit.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lib. <hi>3.</hi> epiſt. <hi>64.</hi> Bellarmine wrot a booke of the freedöe of prieſts from temporall Lords. <hi>Ad Mauritium Imperatorem.</hi>
                  </note> Chriſt hath given power vnto the Emperour to beare rule, not onely ouer ſouldiers, but alſo ouer Prieſts.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Et Imperatori obedientiam praebui, &amp; pro Deo, quod ſenſi minime tacui.</hi> I haue ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed my duty towards my Lord the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, and touching God I haue not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed what I thought.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Valdè mihi durum videtur, ut ab eius (Chriſti) ſervitio milites ſuos prohibeat,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lib. <hi>2.</hi> indict. <hi>11.</hi> epiſt. <hi>103.</hi> Who ſeeth not that the power which Gregory acknowledgeth to be in the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour is as eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentially ouer the Clergie, as ouer the ſouldiers.</note> 
                  <hi>qui ei Imperatori Mauritio) &amp; omnia tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buat,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:20803:38"/>&amp; dominari non ſolum militibus, ſed etiam Sacerdotibus conceſſit.</hi> It ſeemeth ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry hard vnto mee, that he ſhould forbid his ſouldiers the ſeruice of him, (viz. Chriſt)<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> who hath giuen him (the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour <hi>Mauritius)</hi> all things, and granted him not onely to rule ouer ſouldiers, but alſo ouer Prieſts.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>De qua re,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">lib. 7. epiſt. 1. ad Sabinianum diaconum.</note> 
                  <hi>isnum eſt, quod breviter ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geras ſereniſſimis dominis noſtris, quia ſi ego ſervus eorum in morte Long abardorum me miſcere voluiſſem; hodie Longabardorum gens, nec Regem, nec duces, nec comites ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beret. at<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> in ſumma confuſione diviſa eſſet; ſed quia Deum timeo in mortem cuiuſlibet hominis me miſcere formido.</hi> Touching which buſineſſe (ſaith <hi>Gregory)</hi> there is one thing which you may quickly deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to our noble Lords, becauſe if I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their ſervant, would haue mingled my ſelf in the ſlaughter of the <hi>Lumbards;</hi> the people of the <hi>Lumbards</hi> had had at this day neither King, nor Duke, nor Earle, and had beene divided into great confuſion. But becauſe I feare God, I do tremble to mingle my ſelfe into the death of any man.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="Bernard" type="patristic_quotations">
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:20803:38"/>
            <head>
               <hi>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>.</hi> Bernard. <hi>THE PREROGATIVE</hi> of Chriſt to be ſevered from ſinners is common with him vnto none of the ſons of <hi>Adam,</hi> no not to the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irgin <hi>Mary,</hi> although the Papiſts would exempt her from being conceiued in ſinne.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>^<seg rend="decorInit">t</seg> 
               <hi>Bernard</hi> writing to the Canons of Lions in France, touching the ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebration of the Feaſt of the Virgin <hi>Maries</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception, which was then creeping in, reproueth it in theſe words, <hi>Quamobrem et ſi quibus vel paucis filiorum hominum datum eſt cum ſanctitaete naſci,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epiſt. 174. ad Canonic. Lug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dunenſ.</note> 
               <hi>non tamen concipi: ut uni ſanè ſervaretur ſancti praerogativa conceptus, qui omnes ſanctificaret: ſoliss<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> abſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> peccato veniens, purgationem faceret peccatorum.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to whom or to how few ſoeuer of the ſonnes of men it be giuen to be borne holy, yet are they not ſo conceived: that the prerogatiue of an holy conception
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:20803:39"/>might be reſerved vnto one, who ſhould make all holy; and who alone comming without ſinne, ſhould make the purgati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for ſinne. Onely therefore our Lord Ieſus was conceived by the holy Ghoſt, becauſe hee alone was holy, before his conception; who beeing onely ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted, he looketh that all the reſidue of <hi>Adams</hi> children every one, ſhould humbly and truly confeſſe of himſelfe, ſaying,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51, 5.</note> 
               <hi>I was ſhapen in wickednes, and in ſin hath my mother conceived mee. Cum haec ita ſe habeant: quaenam iam erit feſtive ratio conceptionis.</hi> Since theſe things are thus, what ground hath the celebrating of her conception?</p>
            <p>In another place ſpeaking of the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie of Gods eternall predeſtination of the Saints, before all worlds, &amp; of death, running over all, he hath theſe words, <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne quo generalis velamine confuſionis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Super Cant: Serm. 78.</note> 
               <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo filiorum hominum intravit hanc vitam, uno ſanè excepto, qui ingreditur ſine macu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la.</hi> Without which veile of generall confuſion,<note place="margin">The reward of ſin is death: She died. <hi>Ergo</hi> ſhee ſinned.</note> none of the ſonnes of men entred into this life: one onely ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted, who entred without ſpot, whoſe
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:20803:39"/>name is <hi>Emanuell.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The Catholike Church which we beleeue in the Creede, is the whole company of the Elect only.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>SAne ſecundùm praedeſtinationem nunqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Eccleſia electorum penes Deum non fuit.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Super Cant: Serm. 78.</note> 
                  <hi>Simiratur hoc infidelis, audiat quod magis miretur, nunquam non grata extitit, nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam non dilecta. Nec dubium, quin voce omnium electorum iſta dicantur, ET IP<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SI ECCLESIA S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NT.</hi> Surely (ſaith he) according to Gods predeſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,<note place="margin">The Church of the Elect was predeſtinated by God through Chriſt, before the foundation of the world. And all the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect are that Church. <hi>Epheſ. cap. 1.</hi> Serm. <hi>79.</hi>
                  </note> the Church of the Elect was alwaies with him. If he that beleeueth not, marvel at this, let him heare that which he may more marveil at, it was never but pleaſing vnto him, never but beloved. Neither is there any doubt, but thoſe things are ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> (Eph. 1.) in the voyce of all the Elect, <hi>And they are the Church.</hi> In the next following he ſaith, <hi>Non defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit genus Chriſtianum, nec fides de terra, nec charitas de Eccleſia, &amp;c.</hi> Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doth not faile,<note place="margin">The Church of the Elect is heere deſcribed, which onely is built vpon a Rock. And Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard calleth Chriſt the Rock, on which the Church is built, not Peter, or the Pope. Can theſe words bee vnderſtood to be ſpoken but of the Elect, and of them onely. <hi>In Iob. lib. 28. cap. 9.</hi>
                  </note> neither doth faith fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the earth, nor charity from the Church. The floods came, the windes blew, and
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:20803:40"/>ruſhed againſt it, and yet it did not fall, <hi>becauſe it was built vpon a Rocke, for the Rocke was Chriſt.</hi> Therefore, neither by pratling of the Philoſophers, nor cavils of Heretickes, nor ſwords of Tyrants, can it, or ſhal it at any time be ſeparated from the loue of God, which is in Ieſus Chriſt; ſo ſtrongly doth his ſoule hold him, whó it loueth, ſo good it is for him to cleaue vnto God.</p>
               <p>The like is taught by <hi>Gregory</hi> the great, who within the circuit of the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Church</hi> comprehendeth all the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect, and excludeth all the reprobate. And draweth a ſimilitude from the Temple of God, and the court without the Temple.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Revel.</hi> 11. <hi>verſe</hi> 1.2.</note> The one whereof Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> in the Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation was bid to meete and to caſt the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther out. For the Iewiſh Temple was di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided into three parts,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> the body of the Temple, which is called the court, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>into every man entred; <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> the holy places where the Levites were,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> and the holieſt of all,<note place="margin">So when wee ſpeake of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Catholike Church, we caſt out the repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate, and num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber onely the Elect.</note> whereinto the High-Prieſt entred once a yeere. In reſpect therefore of the two later, the firſt is ſaid to be caſt out, becauſe as a thing prophane it is neglec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:20803:40"/>when the Temple is meaſured.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>There are no paſſions nor ſatisfactions of the Saints, whereby themſelues can merit; or that belong to the treaſure of the Church, to be communicated by Indulgences to others.</head>
               <p>This devout &amp; religious man writing <hi>de quadruplici debito</hi> of a fourefold debt,<note place="margin">Bern. ſerm. de quadruplic. officio.</note> which all men are liable vnto, and none able to ſatisfie; And after ſpeech had, of the loue of Chriſt to ſinfull man, and of the Ioyes of Heauen prepared for man re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penting, breaking out againſt all <hi>ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,</hi> entreth into theſe words. <hi>O ſi cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noviſſes &amp; in quam multa &amp; quam multis debeas, videres quam nihil ſit quod facis, quam nec inter minima numerandum ad comparationem debitorum tuorum.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">O if the caſe ſo ſtand, that we owe more then we are able to performe, how ſhall it goe with our workes of ſupererogation?</note> O man (ſaith hee) if thou diddeſt know how much, and to whom thou oweſt, thou wouldeſt ſee <hi>that that is nothing which thou doeſt,</hi> neither not to bee reckoned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the very leaſt, in compariſon of thy
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:20803:41"/>debts. As there is no proportion, between ſomething and nothing; ſo hath our life no equality to our Saviours, ſeeing there is none worthier then his, nor none more wretched then ours. How ſhall I ſatisfie, when I am conſtrained to pay my debt to the vttermoſt farthing? All therefore that I am, I owe to him, from whom as from a Lord, who made me, I haue all;<note place="margin">Remember Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob Geneſ <hi>32.10.</hi> he confeſſeth that he was not worthy of the leaſt of Gods tempornll mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies: how much leſſe are the Saints worthy of eternall.</note> who doth me good, who miniſtreth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to mee the influence of the Starres; the temperature of the Aire; the fruitfulneſſe of the Earth; and the plentie of Fruit. Let no man thinke that I am carried with ſo great madneſſe as heere to make mentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of my ſmall mite, much leſſe to reckon it. And then concludeth. <hi>Quis amplius ergo grunniet dicens; nimium laboramus, nimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um ieiunamus, nimium vigilamus, cum nec mille ſimae imo nec minimae parti, debitorum ſuorum valeat respondere?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">No mans ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings do abound, or over flow to ſatisfie for ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</note> Who therefore dare from henceforth complaine and ſay, wee labour too much, faſte too much, watch too much, when hee cannot an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere the thouſand part, nay not the leaſt part of his debt.</p>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:20803:41"/>
               <p>Againe ſpeaking of the tenne Virgins in the Goſpell, expounding theſe words,<note place="margin">Bern. Serm. de virginibus. <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.8.</note> 
                  <hi>Giue vs of your oyle,</hi> ſaith, <hi>Stulta petitio, vix iuſtus ſalvabitur, vix ſanctis iuſtitiae ſuae oleum ſufficit ad ſalutem, quanto minus &amp; ſibi &amp; proximis.</hi> A fooliſh requeſt, the righteous ſhall ſcarce be ſaved,<note place="margin">The virgins iu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice or righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, is little enough for the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues.</note> the oyle of their owne righteouſneſſe hardly ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the Saints to ſalvation, how much leſſe themſelues &amp; their neighbors. <hi>Noc, Daniel, Iob,</hi> ſhall not deliver a ſonne or daughter, <hi>Ezech.</hi> 14.18: but like as the ſoule, that ſinneth, ſhal die. <hi>Ezech.</hi> 18.20. <hi>Sic anima quae inſtitiam fecerit, ſola ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vabitur.</hi> So that ſoule that doth righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, onely ſhall be ſaved.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">De verb. lib. lob. cap. 5. in ſex tribulat.</note>Againe, ſpeaking of the firſt and ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d <hi>Adam,</hi> ſaith, <hi>Sola nimirum ſecundi Adae tribulatio purgat, quos contaminavit offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſio ſola prioris, non quod propria cuiquam ſufficere poſſit ſatisfactio. Quid enim eſt omnis poenitentianoſtra, niſi quod ſi non co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patimur, omninò non poſſumus conreguare.</hi> It is the onely ſuffering of the ſecond <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> that purgeth vs, whom the onely of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> did defile. I ſay not that any mans owne ſatiſſaction can
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:20803:42"/>ſuffice him; for what is all our repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, but onely<note n="*" place="margin">In the middeſt of our repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance or penance wee muſt hope ſor pardon only by the ſaith of Jeſus Chriſt: yet in weeping for our ſinnes, in bearing our croſſe, in mortifying our members, in offering our ſelues a ſacrifice to God, we become like vnto Chriſt in ſuffering, and ſo are fitted to raigne with him: but the purging vs from ſin, muſt be reſerved to the blood of Chriſt alone.</note> that if we ſuffer not with him, we cannot raigne with him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Man now in his corrupt nature, hath of himſelfe no power of freewill, in good and holy actions; but there is from <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> laid vpon him a neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of ſinning; but yet without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Curet autem haec agere non minus ſuavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter quam fortiter,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">De grat. &amp; lib. arbit. poſt me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium.</note> 
                  <hi>hoc eſt non ex triſtitia aut ex neceſſitate, (quod eſt initium non ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitudo ſapientiae) ſed prompta &amp; alacrivo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntate, quod facit ſacrificium acceptum, quoniam hilarem datorem diligit Deus.</hi> Let a man ſo regard theſe things, that he doe them no leſſe willingly than reſolvedly, not grudgingly, or of neceſſitie, which is the beginning, not the fulneſſe of wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome)
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:20803:42"/>but with a ready &amp; willing mind, becauſe GOD loueth a chearefull giuer. And ſhall he in all things follow wiſdom, while hee re ſolutely withſtandeth vices, and ſweetly obtaineth peace in conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: But certainely looke, by whoſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample we are ſtirred vp to thoſe things, euen his aide and helpe we neede, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by wee may bee made conformable to him through it, and be changed into the ſame Image from glory vnto glory,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.18.</note> 
                  <hi>as by the Spirit of the Lord. Ergo ſi à Domini Spiritu, iam non à libero arbitrio, &amp;c.</hi> Therefore, if by the Spirit of the Lord,<note place="margin">The will of man by nature, can not chuſe but to doe evill, which is a neceſſitie not of coaction, but of deprava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> then not by freewill. Let no man then thinke it is called <hi>freewill,</hi> becauſe it hath equall power to good and evill; ſince in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede it may fall of it ſelfe, but not riſe without the <hi>Spirit of God:</hi> Otherwiſe nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther God nor the holy Angels, being ſo good, that they cannot be evill; nor the Angels that fell, who are ſo evil, that now they cannot bee good, could be ſaid to haue freewill. But therefore it is called free, becauſe none can be good or evill <hi>niſi volens,</hi> but willingly. Againe. <hi>Porro, ube voluntas, ibi libertas;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Super Cant. Serm. 81.</note> 
                  <hi>quod tamen dice
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:20803:43"/>de naturali, non de spirituali, qua libertate (ut dicit Apoſtolus) Chriſtus nos libera. vit.</hi> Where will is, there is libertie, which yet I ſpeake of the naturall,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Galat.</hi> 4.31.</note> and not of the ſpiritual; by which liberty (as the Apoſtle ſaith) Chriſt hath made vs free; for of that he himſelfe ſaith the ſame,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.17.</note> 
                  <hi>Where the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of the Lord is, there is libertie.</hi> So is the ſoule by a wonderfull and vnhappy free neceſſitie,<note place="margin">Thereremaineth no freeneſſe of will vnto good in man, but only a voluntary promptneſſe and inclination to evill without conſtraint. <hi>In Feſto Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecoſt. ſerm. 1.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>both bound, and free,</hi> bound be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of neceſſity, free becauſe it is volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary. And that which is more wonderfull and more miſerable; the more guilty, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe free; and the more free becauſe guilty, and by this the more bound be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe free.</p>
               <p>Againe. <hi>Initium revertendi ad Deum poenitentia eſt, quam ſine dubio ſpiritus ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratur, non noſter ſed Dei, id<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>, &amp; certa ratio docet, &amp; confirmat authoritas.</hi> The begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of our conuerſion to God, is by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, which without doubt the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit doth worke in vs, not ours but Gods Spirit, and this both reaſon doth teach, &amp; authority confirme. Who then, when he commeth benummed or frozen to the fire, and ſhall bee made warme or hor,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:20803:43"/>doth doubt that he was heated by the fire which he could not haue beene without it. So he that is firſt dead in iniquity,<note place="margin">If we be dead in ſin, where is our freewill to good?</note> if af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward hee bee ſet on fire by the heate of repentance; doeth know and finde, that another ſpirit beſides his owne, which doth reproue and diſcerne his, hath come vnto him.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">De grat. &amp; li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber. arbitr. an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te medium.</note>Again, ſpeaking of our firſt Parent <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> in Paradiſe, and both of what he had, and of what he there loſt, ſaith, <hi>Corruit autem de poſſe non peccare, in non poſſe non peccare, &amp;c.</hi> He fell from his not being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to ſinne, to his not being able to doe any thing but ſinne, hauing altogether loſt the libertie of taking aduice &amp; coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, as alſo that which he had of forbea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to ſinne. And this loſſe happened vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him by the abuſing of the libertie of his will. Being fallen from his will, it is not ſtill remaining free for him to raiſe vp himſelfe again by the ſame. For although at this day he would doe it, yet the caſe ſo ſtandeth with him, as that it is not in his power not to ſinne. It muſt be Chriſt that muſt inſpire him, and indue him with new vertue by his reſtauration, that the
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:20803:44"/>Lord may transforme vs into his Image how be it even then <hi>our perfection commeth not in this life, but in the life to come.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Againe.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 20. <hi>verſe</hi> 4.</note> Vpon this Text. <hi>Praeveniſti e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um in benedictionibus dulcedin is.</hi> Thou do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt prevent him with bleſſings of good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſaith,<note place="margin">Parv. Serm. in 39. Serm.</note> 
                  <hi>Triplex nobis neceſſaria eſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedictio, &amp;c.</hi> Three bleſſings there are, which are neceſſary for vs, 1. that of <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venting,</hi> 2, that of <hi>helping,</hi> 3. <hi>ending.</hi> The firſt is of <hi>mercy,</hi> the ſecond is of <hi>grace;</hi> the third is of <hi>glory.</hi> He doth prevent our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation by his mercy, hee helpeth our converſation by his grace, he doth acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh our ending with glory. Vnleſſe the Lord doth giue theſe three bleſſings,<note place="margin">noſtra terra.</note> our bodies can bring forth no fruit. Neither can we beginne any good thing, before wee be prevented by mercy; or doe any good thing vntill we be holpen by grace, nor end in goodneſſe, vntill wee be filled with glory.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Againſt the doctrine of Merit, as it is taught in the Church of Rome now.</head>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:20803:44"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Teſtimonium conſcientiae noſtra in tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus conſiſtere credo.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In annunt, beat. Mariae Serm. 1.</note> I beleeue (ſaith he) that the witneſſe of our conſcience ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in theſe three. It is firſt of all neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to beleeue, that wee cannot haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſin, but by the mercy of God; Then that wee can haue no good worke, except he giue it. Laſtly,<note place="margin">Eternall life is freely giuen not purchaſed by any works. Sins not impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, are as thogh they had never bin commited.</note> that eternall life is purchaſed by no merits, but is freely giuen. For who can make that cleane, which is conceiued of vncleane ſeed, but he that is onely cleane; truely that which is done, cannot be vndone: but when hee imputeth it not, it ſhalbe as though it had not beene done. For touching good workes it is moſt certaine that no man hath them of himſelfe. If mans nature could not ſtand, when it was yet perfect, how much leſſe can it raiſe it ſelfe by it ſelfe being now corrupt.<note n="*" place="margin">The Rhemiſts in their anno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations on the New Teſtament doe nothing ſo much as contrary this do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine pleading their merits and workes to be meritorious. In Mathew, c. <hi>6.</hi> v <hi>4.</hi> in Marke <hi>12.</hi> v. <hi>11.</hi> that workes are the very cauſe of ſalvation, in Rom. <hi>2.</hi> v. <hi>6.</hi> The Ioyof Heauen is the hire and wages for works, which workes can be no other but the valure, deſert, price, worth and merit of the ſame. In <hi>1.</hi> cor. <hi>3.</hi> v. <hi>8.</hi> Heaven is our owne right, bargained or wrought for, and accordingly paid vnto vs as our hire, at the day of iudgement. In <hi>2.</hi> Tim: <hi>4.</hi> v. <hi>8.</hi>
                  </note> Neither are
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:20803:45"/>the merits of men ſuch, that life euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting is due for them by right, or that God ſhould be ſaid to doe iniury, except he yeeld it them.</p>
               <p>Againe he ſaith, <hi>Ego ſidenter quod ex me mihi deeſt, uſurpo nothi ex viſceribus do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini, quoniam miſericordia effluunt, nee deſunt foramina per quae effluant.</hi> Surely, whatſoever is wanting to me of my ſelfe, I boldly take it vnto me out of the bowels of my Lord, becauſe they flow out with mercy, neither wanteth there any wayes by which they may flow. My merit is the Lords mercy. I am not altogether poore in merit. ſo long as he is not poore in mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy. And if the Lord be rich in mercy, then am I alſo no leſſe in merit. And if the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of the Lord be fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euerlaſting to ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting, I wil ſing the mercies of the Lord for ever.<note place="margin">Imputatiue iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice is eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, and inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwne. <hi>De grat. &amp; lib. arbit. in fine.</hi>
                  </note> What ſhal I ſing mine own righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes? O Lord I wil reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber thy righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes onely. For that is my righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, becauſe thou art made by God righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes vnto me. And vpon that Text of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Paul,</hi> 2. Tim. 1.12. <hi>Scio cui credidi, &amp; certus ſum, quia potens eſt depoſitu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> meu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vare.</hi> I know who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I haue beleeved, and am
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:20803:45"/>perſwaded,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Depoſitum meum</hi> that which I haue committed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>him. <hi>2.</hi> Tim. <hi>4.8.</hi> The crowne of glory is the iuſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of the righteous man: yet not by vertue of his righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and deſert, but by the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull promiſe of Almightie God. Look thoſe notes of the Rhemiſts ſet downe in the margent before, at this marke. and tell me, how they agree with Bernard here. Workes are the cauſe; the very cauſe of getting heauen, No ſaith Bern. They are the way thither, not the cauſe of our raigning there.</note> that he is able to keepe that which I haue committed to him againſt that day. He calleth (ſaith <hi>Bernard</hi>) the promiſe of God his <hi>depoſitum</hi> &amp; becauſe he beleeued him that promiſed, hee doth confidently make mention of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe. A promiſe indeed of mercy, but to be paid in iuſtice. This is therefore that which S. <hi>Paul</hi> expected, <hi>a crown of iuſtice,</hi> but of <hi>Gods iuſtice,</hi> not his <hi>owne.</hi> For it is iuſt that God paye what hee oweth; and he oweth what hee hath promiſed. And this is the iuſtice of which the Apoſtle preſumeth <hi>even the promiſe of God,</hi> leaſt deſpiſing that, he might eſtabliſh his own and ſo bee ſubiect to the iuſtice of God. And then in the ende, hee knitteth vp the whole tract with this excellent ſaying, <hi>St proprie appellentur ea qua dicimus noſtra merita &amp;c.</hi> But if wee ſpeake properly of thoſe things which wee call our merits, <hi>they are certaine ſeed grounds of our hope; incitements of our loue, tokens of our ſecret predestination, foretokens of our future hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe, The way to the kingdome, not the cauſe of our raigning, or of our hauing the kingdome.</hi> Furthermore whom hee iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:20803:46"/>
                  <hi>not whom he findeth iuſt,</hi> thoſe he glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifieth.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">In dedic. Eccleſ. Serm. <hi>5.</hi> Mat. <hi>16.</hi> Thou art Chriſt the ſonne of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving God.</note>Againe, ſpeaking of Chriſts ſpeech in the 16. of <hi>Mat.</hi> to S. <hi>Peter Beatus es Simo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Barjona, nec multo poſt, vade retro ſatana.</hi> Bleſſed art thou Simon Barjona; and a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle after. Get thee behind me ſathan, ſaith <hi>unde Barjona?</hi> How was it that he was cald <hi>Barjona?</hi> But becauſe not fleſh and bloud but the father by who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſpake it, revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led it vnto him. How is it that he was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Sathan?</hi> but becauſe hee ſavoured of the things, that were of man, and not of God. Now, if in both theſe conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, wee ſhall diligently looke into our ſelues; yea how in the one wee are no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, and how exalted in the other, <hi>I thinke our glorying ought to bee temperate; but peradventure it is more increaſed, yet is it ſtrengthned, that we ſhould not reioyce in our ſelues, but in God.</hi> Neither am I for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getfull, but with feare and reverence I ſay <hi>Nos ſumus. Nos inquam ſumus ſed in corde Des.</hi> Wee are, we are I ſay, worthy but in the minde of God; we are worthie, but by his acceptance,<note place="margin">Gods acceptance not our worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſse.</note> not by our worthineſſe. It followes, <hi>Quod ſi nos ex puerili animoſitate
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:20803:46"/>gratis ſalvari nolumus.</hi> If wee of childiſh ſtomacke will not bee ſaued <hi>freely,</hi> iuſtly are we not ſaued at all. The diſſembling of our miſery excludeth mercy,<note place="margin">Read O man in thine own heart ſay the Rhemiſts and thou ſhalt finde that thy workes are fully worthy of ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting life. Rhem teſtam. annot. <hi>2.</hi> Tim. <hi>4.</hi> Serm. in Cant. <hi>68.</hi>
                  </note> neither hath God (acceptance or) vouchſafing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny place where preſumption is of our worthineſſe. <hi>Lege homo in corde tuo &amp;c.</hi> Read O man in thine owne heart, read within thy ſelfe, concerning thy ſelfe: the witneſſe of truth, <hi>and thou wilt iudge thy ſelfe vnworthy of this common light.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Againe, <hi>Quid de merit is ſolicita ſit Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſia, cui de propoſito dei firmior ſuppetit ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curior<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> gloria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>di ratio.</hi> Why is the Church ſo carefull touching merits, who hath a more ſure and ſecure cauſe of reioycing by reaſon of the purpoſe of God. It is not for thee to aske, by what merits we hope for good things;<note place="margin">No ſay the Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts, you muſt knowe that good works be ſo farre meritorious that God ſhould bee vniuſt, if he ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred not heauen for the ſame. Annot. Heb. <hi>6.</hi> v. <hi>10.</hi>
                  </note> ſeeing thou heareſt by the Prophet, <hi>Not for your ſakes, but for mine owne ſake will I doe it, ſaith the Lord.</hi> It ſufficeth for merit to knowe that me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits are not ſufficient. Bee carefull to haue merits; when thou haſt them, knowe that they be giuen thee, but for fruit thereof <hi>hope for the mercy of God.</hi> The want of merits is a pernicious povertie, and the
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:20803:47"/>preſumption of the ſpirit, is deceitfull ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Ser. <hi>73.</hi> in Cant. Where are the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verplus of the ſufferings and ſatisfactions of the Saints to be applied to others when the moſt righteous muſt pray, for the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giueneſſe of their owne ſinnes? In Pſal. qui ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitat. ſerm.</note>Still hee followeth the ſame doctrine, <hi>Opus ita<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> habent &amp; ſancti pro peccatis ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orare, vt de miſericordia ſalui fiant propria iustitiae non fidentes. Omnes enim pecca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt &amp; egent miſericordia Dei.</hi> Even the Saints haue need to entreat for their ſins, that by his mercy they may be ſaved, not truſting to their own righteouſneſſe; For all haue ſinned, and ſtand in need of the mercy of God. <hi>Quid enim ſtultius quam habitare in domo vix adhuc inchoata? con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſummaſſe te putas? at cum conſummaverit homo tunc incipit, &amp;c.</hi> What more fooliſh is it (ſaith hee) then to dwell in an houſe ſcarce as yet begun? Doſt thou think that thou haſt finiſhed it? But when man hath finiſhed it, then doth he but begin. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, this dwelling is altogether ruinous, it hath more need to be vnderſet &amp; prop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, then dwelt in. Is not our life fraile &amp; vncertaine? It is of neceſſity that whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is founded vpon it,<note place="margin">Who can thinke to ſet a ſure buil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding vpon a tot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on?</note> bee like vnto it; for who doth truſt a ſure building vpon a tottering foundation? <hi>Dangerous is the dwelling of them that truſt in thir merits, it
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:20803:47"/>is dangerous becauſe it is ruinous.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Serm. ibid. <hi>15.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Hoc e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim totum hominis meritum, ſi totam spem ſuam ponat in illo, qui totum hominem ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vum fecit.</hi> For this is the whole merit of man, to put his whole truſt in him, who hath wholy ſaued man. <hi>Orate ſalvatore<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 310.</note> 
                  <hi>qui non vult mortem peccatoris, vt tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtivum iam exitum non differat, ſed cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diat. Curate munire votis calcaneum nudu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> meritis, vt is qui inſideatur invenire non poſſit vnde figat dentem &amp; vulnus infligit.</hi> I beſeech you friends pray the ſavior for me, who will not the death of a ſinner, that he delay not this timely departure of mine, but keepe it. I deſire you to ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then with your prayers my heele <hi>(that is the ending of my life)</hi> which is void of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, that he that layeth wait may not finde wherein to fix his tooth there by to giue a wound.</p>
               <p>To conclude, let that ſuffice,<note place="margin">Serm. <hi>13.</hi> ſuper Cant.</note> which this holy man Bernard; (reciting many wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy acts done in the olde Teſtament by the worthies of thoſe times <hi>David, Ioſua, lepthe, Gedeon, Sampſon, Iudith, Iudas Machabaeus;</hi> and how that none of theſe imparted their glory to any other) infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:20803:48"/>ſtrongly, <hi>Quid minus ab his omnibus conditor omnium fecit, quo minus &amp; ipſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beat gloriari ſingulariter?</hi> What hath the maker of all things done leſſe then any of theſe, that hee ſhould glory alone, leſſe then they? He alone hath triumphed over the enemies; hee alone hath deliuered the captiues; and ſhall hee haue a partner in the glory?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>It is impoſſible for any man how regenerate ſoever to fulfill the whole law, now in his corrupt nature, becauſe it ſaith, Curſed is every ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that continueth not in all things that are written therein.<note place="margin">Sup. Cant. ſer. <hi>58</hi> The Law (if J may ſo speake) giueth Law to the whole man, to al his thoughts words, &amp; deeds, and taketh ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception againſt any thing either inwardly or out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly, whereby we ſtep aſide fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the rule thereof.</note>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>QVantumlibet in hoc corpore manens profeceris, erras ſi vitia putas emor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuae, &amp; non magis ſuppreſſa: velis nolis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra fines tuos habitat Iebuſaem, ſubiugari poteſt ſed non exterminari. Scto (inquit) quiae non habitat in me bonum. Parum eſt niſi &amp; malum, ineſſe fateatur.</hi> How much ſoever thou doſt profit whilſt thou abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:20803:48"/>in this body, thou art deceaued,<note place="margin">Vices are not dead in vs. As the Rhemiſts be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore pleaded no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more then their merits: ſo ſay they in this queſtion, of ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling Gods co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements through true in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herent iuſtice. Annot. Mat. <hi>5.</hi> v. <hi>21.</hi> &amp; <hi>11.</hi> v. <hi>30.</hi> and, goodme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doe keepe all Gods commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements, againe, the keeping and doing of the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendements is properly our iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification. In Luk. c. <hi>1.</hi> v. <hi>6.</hi> It is not impoſſible to keepe that Commandement of louing God with al our hart. Luc. <hi>10.</hi> v. <hi>28.</hi> &amp; <hi>1.</hi> Ioh. <hi>3.</hi> v. <hi>22.</hi> Cant. Ser. <hi>50.</hi> S. Bernard here doth not only affirme the impoſſibilitie of ful &amp; perfect keeping of the law, but giueth reaſons alſo, why God notwithſtanding held it profitable for vs that he ſhould giue the Law, and in every point ſpeaketh fully and expreſſely the ſame that wee doe.</note> if thou thinke that vices are dead in thee, &amp; not rather ſuppreſſed. Whether thou wilt or no the <hi>Iebuſite</hi> will dwell within thy coaſts, he may be brought vnder, but not vtterly baniſhed. I knowe (ſaith S. <hi>Paul</hi>) that in me dwelleth no good thing. That is but a ſmall matter, except hee alſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, that evill was preſent with him. Hee ſaith, <hi>Not the good which I would doe, that doe I; but I doe the evill which I hate.</hi> But if I do that which I hate, it is no more I that doe it, but ſinne that dwelleth in me. Ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther if thou dareſt preferre thy ſelf before the Apoſtle (whoſe ſaying this is) or elſe confeſſe with him, that thou alſo doſt not want vices.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quomodo ergo iubenda fuit, quae imple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da nullo modo erat? Aut ſi placet tibi magis de affectuali datum fuiſſe mandatum, non inde contendo, dum modo acquieſcas &amp; tu mihi quod minime in vita iſta ab aliquo ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minum poſſit vel potuerit adimpleri.</hi> How
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:20803:49"/>was the law to be commanded,<note place="margin">What can bee, ſaid more plainly againſt the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts now, then this? See the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Rhe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>miſts. If the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements (ſay they) be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to bee kept, Chriſt had mocked and not taught the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer and others, when he propou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded the keeping of them, for the meane to obtain life everlaſting. Annot. in Luc. c. <hi>10.</hi> v. <hi>28.</hi> No, ſaith S. Bernard, God by comman ding things im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible, doth not thereby make man a tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſour, but hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleth him, to the intent that man perceauing his owne defect might in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> his righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es by works, fly vnto Gods mercy &amp; grace.</note> which ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by no meanes be fulfilled? or if thou ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thinke that the commandement was giuen for the ruling of our affections, I will not herevpon ſtriue; ſo that thou alſo doe yeeld vnto me, <hi>that in this life it nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can, or over could bee fulfilled of any man. Quis enim ſibi arrogare id audeat, quodſe Paulus ipſe fatetur non comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſſe?</hi> For who dare arrogate that to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, which Paul himſelfe confeſſeth, hee had not comprehended? <hi>Nec latuit pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptorem praecepti pondus, hominum exce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere vires.</hi> Neither was the commander ignorant, that the waight of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment exceeded mans ſtrength, but he iudged it to be profitable, that thereby they might be put in minde of their owne inſufficiencie, and ſo might knowe that they ought according to their power la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to the end of righteouſneſſe. <hi>Ergo mandando impoſſibilia non praevaricatores homines fecit, ſed humiles, vt omne os ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruatur, &amp; ſubdit us fiat omnis mundus Deo: quia ex operibus legis non iustificabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur omnis caro coram illo.</hi> Therefore by commanding things impoſſible, he made
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:20803:49"/>men not tranſgreſſors but humble; that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very mouth be ſtopped, and all the world made ſubiect vnto God, becauſe that by the works of the law, no fleſh ſhall be iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified before him; for wee receauing the Commandements, and feeling our owne want, will cry vnto heauen, and God will haue mercy vpon vs: <hi>Et ſciemus in illa die quia non ex operibus iuſtitia qua fecimus nos, ſed ſecundum ſuam miſericordiam ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vos nos fecit.</hi> And that wee may knowe at that day, that not for the workes of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe which wee haue done, but of his owne mercy hath he ſaued vs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Infelix ego home,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">De advent. dom Ser. <hi>6.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>quis me liberabit de corpore mortis huius?</hi> Vnhappy man that I am (ſaith S. <hi>Paul</hi>) who ſhall deliuer mee from this body of death. For hee did cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainely knowe that hee could not before be deliuered from that naughty root that cleaueth to the fleſh, and from the law of ſinne, which is in our members, vntill hee were diſſolued from this body, wherevp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it was that he deſired to be diſſolved, and to be with Chriſt, knowing that ſin which worketh divorce betweene God and vs, cannot vtterly be taken away, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:20803:50"/>till we be deliuered from this body:<note place="margin">Marc. <hi>9.</hi> In Ser. omnium Sanct. Serm. <hi>1.</hi> Conſider I pray thee Reader, how this text of Bern. agreeth with theſe notes of the Rhemiſts. Chriſtians are truely iuſt, and haue in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues inherent iuſtice by doing Gods comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts in Mat. c. <hi>5.</hi> v. <hi>21.</hi> The keeping and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements is properly our iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification. in Luc. <hi>1.</hi> v. <hi>6.</hi> &amp; <hi>75.</hi> No, ſaith Bernard, all our righteouſneſſe is as a ſtained &amp; defiled cloth.</note> you haue heard of one whome our Lord diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſeſſed of a Deuill, and how tearing &amp; re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ting him the Deuill departed. Therfore I ſay vnto you, that kind of ſin which ſo often doeth trouble vs <hi>(I mean our concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcence and euill deſires)</hi> ought indeed to be repreſſed, &amp; may by the grace of God, that it rainge not in vs, neither that we giue our members weapons of iniquitie to ſin, &amp; in that reſpect, there is noe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nation to thoſe that are in Ieſus Chriſt. <hi>Sed non eiicitur niſi in morte:</hi> but that ſin is not caſt forth but in death when we dot ſo rent it, that the ſoule be ſeperated fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the body.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Beati qui eſuriunt, et ſitiunt iuſtitiam, que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niam ipſi ſaturabuntur; ſed quid poteſt eſſe omnis iuſtitia noſtra coram Deo?</hi> Bleſſed are they that hunger and thirſt for right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eouſneſſe ſake, for they ſhall be ſatiſſfied. But what ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all our righteouſneſſe be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God? ſhall it not according to the prophet be accounted as a moſt filthy &amp; defiled cloth? &amp; if all our rigthteouſneſſe be ſtraitly iudged it ſhal be found vniuſt, &amp; haue no force. What therfore ſhal be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:20803:50"/>come of our ſins, when as euen our righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe it ſelfe ſhall not be able to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere for it ſelfe? Therfore earneſtly cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with the Prophet, Enter not into iudgement with thy ſervant O Lord, let vs with all humbleneſſe <hi>run to the throne of mercy which only is able to ſaue our ſouls.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>That faith only iuſtifieth; and that there it an infallible certaintie of ſalvation from confidence of Gods mercy in Chriſt, knowne to a man in his owne conſcience by an ordinary special divine faith.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>COrde creditur adiuſtitiam, ore fit con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſio ad ſalutem.<note place="margin">In vigil. natal. dom. Serm. <hi>1.</hi> in fine.</note> Iuſtitia ſiquidem in corde, panis in domo. Eſt enim iuſtitia pani &amp; beati qui eſuriunt &amp; ſitiunt iuſtitiam, quoniam ipſi ſaturabuntur. Siergo in corde iuſtitia, eſt iuſtitia quae ex fide est. Hac e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim ſola habet gloriam apud Deum. Fit eti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am ore confeſſio ad ſalutem, &amp; ſecurus iam ſuſcipe eum qui in Bethleem Iuda naſeitur Ieſum Chriſtum filium Dei.</hi> With the hart man beleeueth vnto righteouſneſſe, and
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:20803:51"/>with the mouth man confeſſeth to ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.<note place="margin">Faith as it is an inſtrument of ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>prehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding Chriſt to righteouſneſſe and life everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting is alwaies alone, but as it is the way to ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, it is not alone. Rom. <hi>10.10.</hi>
                  </note> Truely righteouſneſſe in the heart, is as bread in the mouth, for righteouſneſſe is bread; and bleſſed are they that hunger and thirſt after righteouſneſſe for they ſhall be ſatisfied. If therefore righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe be in the heart, <hi>it is the righteouſnes that is of faith, for that only hath glory with God:</hi> Let the confeſſion bee alſo in the mouth to ſalvation, and then being ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure, receaue him who was borne in Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thleem Iuda Ieſus Chriſt the ſon of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nam ſibi quidem ipſi fidere,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ibid. Serm. <hi>5.</hi> If there were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herent righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe; man might truſt to himſelfe, but hee may not truſt to himſelfe, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he hath not inherent righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe.</note> 
                  <hi>non fides, ſed perfidiae eſt.</hi> For truely for one to truſt in himſelfe is not of faith, but of vnbeleefe; neither is it confidence for a man to put his truſt in his owne ſelfe, but diffidence &amp; miſtruſt rather. But he is faithfull, who neither truſteth to himſelfe, nor hopeth in himſelfe, but is to himſelfe as a loſt veſſel, ſo looſing his owne life, that he may keep it to everlaſting life.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>At vero iuſtitiae tuae tanta vbi<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> fragra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia spargitur, vt non ſolum iuſtus ſed etiam ipſa dicaris iustitia, &amp; iuſtitia iuſtificans. Tam validus deni<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> es ad iuſtificandum, quam multus ad ignoſcendum. Quamobrem
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:20803:51"/>quiſquis pro peccatis compunctus eſurit,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hunger &amp; thirſt after righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe ſaith he, not inherent righteouſneſſe, but that righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe which conſiſteth in the forgiueneſſe of ſinnes. Idem ibid. Note. Iuſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on before God is no where in al the Scripture a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed to any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vertueſaue only faith, the promiſe of ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is ſomtimes adioyned to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vertues, as fruits and marks of them whom God hath ſaued but never as cauſes thereof. S. Bernard ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth of a righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, that forgiueth ſinnes, and that is not inherent righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, I trow. This is the very forme of our righteouſneſſe, not to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber our offences. Ser. <hi>1.</hi> de annun.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp; ſitit iustitiam, credat in te, qui iuſtific as impium, &amp; ſolam iuſtifieat us per fidem pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem habebit ad Deum.</hi> But indeed ſo ſweet a ſavour of thy righteouſneſſe is every where ſpread abroad, that thou maiſt not only bee called righteous, but righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe it ſelfe, and a iuſtifying righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Furthermore, thou art as able to iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie, as thou art ready to forgiue. Where fore whoſoever inwardly grieued for his ſinne, doth hunger and thirſt after righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, <hi>Let him beleeue in thee who iusti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied the vngodly, and being iuſtified by faith only, he ſhall haue peace with God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Againe in the ſame place, ſpeaking of Chriſt who is our righteouſneſſe ſaith, <hi>Per iuſtitiam deni<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> quea ex fide eſt, ſolvit funes peccatorum GRATIS iuſtificans peccatorem.</hi> By the righteouſneſſe which is of faith, he looſeth the cords of ſinners, FREELY iuſtifying the ſinner. And tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching vs to beleeue in Chriſt ſpeaketh of him, as of a righteouſneſſe <hi>quae delicta do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat,</hi> that forgiueth ſinnes; And wherein that righteouſneſſe doth eſſentially and really conſiſt, he expreſſeth thus, <hi>Delicta
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:20803:52"/>inventutis meae &amp; ignorantias meat ne me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mineris &amp; iuſtus ſum.</hi> Remember not the offences of my youth and my ignorances and I am righteous or iuſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sicredis peccata tua non poſſe deleri niſi ab eo cui ſoli peccasti, &amp; in quem peccatum non cadit, benefacis; ſed adde adhuc, vt &amp; hoc credas, quia per ipſum peccata tibi con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donantur. Hoc eſt teſtimonium quod perhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet in corde ſpiritus ſanctus, dicens dimiſſa ſunt tibi peccata tua.</hi> If thou doſt bele eue, that thy ſinnes cannot be forgiuen, but by him againſt whom thou haſt only ſinned, and on whom ſinne never fell,<note place="margin">The faith wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by a man is tis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified, is ſuch a faith as where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by I beleeue my owne ſalvation.</note> thou doſt well, but adde withall, that thou ſhould<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt beleeue alſo, that by him thy ſinnes are forgiuen thee. This is the witnes that the holy Ghoſt beareth in thy heart ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>thy ſinnes are forgiuen thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Againe,<note place="margin">Epiſt. <hi>107.</hi> Why ſhould not a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beleeue his owne ſalvation, when the ſpirit by faith revealeth to him the purpoſe of God, that he ſhal be ſaued.</note> 
                  <hi>Iuſtus est quis, niſi qui amanti ſe Deo, vicem rependit amoris? quod non fit niſi revelante ſpiritu per fidem homini aeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num dei propoſitum ſuper ſua ſalute futura. Quae ſane revelatio, non eſt aliud quam in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſio gratiae ſpiritualis.</hi> Who is iuſt but hee that returneth loue to God who hath lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved him? which is not done, but when the
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:20803:52"/>ſpirit by faith, revealeth to a man the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall purpoſe of God concerning his own ſalvation to come. <hi>Quae ſane revelatio &amp;c</hi> which revelation is nothing elſe but the infuſion of ſpirituall grace whereby the deeds of the fleſh are mortified, and the man prepared to the kingdome of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which fleſh and bloud inherit not, recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving together in one ſpirit, both whereby he may preſume that he is beloued, and doth alſo loue againe. And this ſecret of <hi>faith</hi> he preſently after ſaith is <hi>fons ſigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, cui alienus non communicat, eſt ſol iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitiae qui timentibus deum tantum oritur.</hi> A ſpring and fountaine ſhut and ſealed vp to be private to themſelues, the ſonne of righteouſneſſe, which doth not ſhine but to them that feare God. And if there bee any that feele not that comfort in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, the Prophet (ſaith he) doth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce of them that they are <hi>gens quae no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> audivit vocem Deiſui,</hi> a people that haue not harkned to the voice of God ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in them.</p>
               <p>And before all this,<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> in the ſame Epiſtle <hi>Sic ad ortum ſolis iuſtitiae ſacramentum abſconditum à ſeculis de praedeſtinatis &amp;
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:20803:53"/>beatificandis emergere aliquanclo incipit ex abyſſo aternitatis, dum quiſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> vocatus per timorem, iuſtificatus per amorem praſumit ſe quo<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> eſſe de numero beatorum, ſciens ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirum quia quos iuſtificavit illos &amp; magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficanit.</hi> So at the riſing of the ſun of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe (in our iuſtification) the ſecret that was hidden from the beginning co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning them that are predeſtinate, and ſhall be bleſſed, beginneth to appeare out of the depth of eternitie, whilſt a man called by the feare of God, and made iuſt by loue, preſumeth that hee is one of the number of the bleſſed, knowing that whom he hath iuſtified, them alſo he hath glorified. For what? hee heareth himſelfe called, when hee is ſtriken with the feare of God, and he feeleth that he is iuſtified, when hee is all beſprinkled with the loue of God, and ſhall he doubt of his glorifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation? he is receaved into favour, hee is advanced, and ſhall he doubt onely of the finiſhing? It followeth, <hi>habes homo huius arcani indicem ſpiritum iuſtificantem, co<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ipſo teſtificantem spiritui tuo quod filius dei &amp; ipſe ſis; agnoſce conſilium Dei in vocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one Dei.</hi> O man thou haſt for thy decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:20803:53"/>of that ſecret <hi>the ſpirit</hi> iuſtifying thee, and thereby teſtifying <hi>to thy Spirit,</hi> that euen thou art the child of God; acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge therefore the counſel of God in thy iuſtificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And this euery one receiveth in his iuſtification, wherein he beginneth to know, as he is known, there being give<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to him to perceive ſomwhat beforeha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of his future bliſſe, even as it hath lien hid from everlaſting in God,<note place="margin">Saint Bernard eſtabliſheth a foreſight of fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture bliſſe.</note> by whom hee was predeſtinate, and ſhall more fully ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare in the ſame God, when hee ſhall make him bleſſed; yet, of which know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of himſelfe, now already perceived in part, he for the time reioycety in hope,<note place="margin">Although a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> muſt not at all times reioyce in ſecurity, as though there were nothing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more to trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble him: but he may be thus far ſecure, as to be without doubt of an happy iſſue &amp; deliverance, and this is the hope that we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce in.</note> but <hi>not in ſecurity</hi> rightly acknowledging himſelfe to be the child, not of wrath, but of grace, he hath the triall &amp; proofe of the fatherly affection of Gods goodneſſe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him, he perceiveth and conſidently reſolveth that he is beloved of God, and preſumeth that he is one of the number of the bleſſed.</p>
               <p>To conclude, this he ſaith of the ſinner caſting away the works of darkenes, and putting on the armour of light, <hi>Gloriari iam incipit,</hi> he now beginneth to glory
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:20803:54"/>beſides hope, in the hope of the glory of the ſons of God;<note place="margin">For all his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall of glorying in ſecurity, yet doth he ever e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſh our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioycing in hope, becauſe much conflict remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth for the at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayning of that which notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly is ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped for.</note> which glory now euen neere at hand hee beholdeth with open face, leaping for ioy at this new light, hee conſidereth and ſaith, <hi>Signatum eſt ſuper nos lumen vultus tui Domine, dediſti laeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam in corde meo.</hi> The light of thy coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance is ſcaled vpon vs O Lord, thou haſt put gladneſſe in my heart. <hi>Iam ſi O bone Pater vermis viliſſimus &amp; odio dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſſimus ſempiterno, tamen confidit amari, quia ſe ſentit amare<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> imo quia ſe amari prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentit non confunditur redamare.</hi> Although moſt gratious Father, he now bee a moſt vile worme, &amp; worthy of euerlaſting ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, yet doth he aſſure himſelfe that hee is beloved, becauſe he feeleth himſelfe to loue; nay becauſe he firſt feeleth himſelf to be beloved; therefore hee is not aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to loue againe.</p>
               <p>Again: <hi>Quis poterit ſalvus eſſe? dicunt diſcipuli Salvatoris.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Serm. 5. in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicatione ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ.</note> 
                  <hi>Apud homines hoc impoſſibile eſt, ſed non apud Deum.</hi> Who ſhalbe ſaved? ſay the Diſciples of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour. This is impoſſible with men, but not with God. This is our whole confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence; this is our onely comfort; this is
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:20803:54"/>the whole meanes of our hope But being ſure of Gods ableneſſe to ſaue vs,<note place="margin">Although by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther meanes wee cannot know whether we be beloved or hated of God; yet by faith and by the ſpirit of God, that ſecret is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed vnto vs, that wee are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued of God &amp; are his children.</note> what do we to be aſſured of his will thereto? For who knoweth whether hee be worthy of loue or hatred? who hath knowen the mind of the Lord, or who hath beene his counſellor? <hi>Hic iam planè fidem nobis ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venire neceſſe eſt.</hi> But heere faith muſt needs helpe vs; heere Gods truth muſt needs be our ſuccour, that that which ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth hid concerning vs in the Heart of God our Father <hi>may by his Spirit be revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vnto vs, and his Spirit by the testimony thereof may perſwade our ſpirits, that wee are the children of God, and that it is done by calling &amp; iuſtifying of vs freely by faith;</hi> in which two there is as it were a certaine middle paſſage, from the eternall prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtination to the glorification which ſhall be heereafter.</p>
               <p>Againe, vpon this Text, <hi>Omnis qui na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus eſt ex Deo, non peccat,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In Septuag. Serm. 1. 1. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 5. <hi>v.</hi> 18.</note> 
                  <hi>ſed generatio coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtis conſervat illum.</hi> Euery one that is borne of God ſinneth not, but the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of God, or he that is begotten of God, doth keepe him, ſaith. <hi>Sed generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem iſtam quis enarrabit?</hi> But who ſhall
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:20803:55"/>declare this generation? who can ſay, I am one of the number of the elect? I am one of the children; The Scripture ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,<note place="margin">This excludeth all apprehenſion of fleſh and bloud, as iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of reaſon or humane knowledge, but the ſecret of the ſpirit is exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth not.</note> Man doth not know whethe hee be worthy of loue or hatred: verily we haue not a certainety, but the boldnes of hope doth comfort vs, leſt we ſhould be alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether grieved with the perplexity of the doubt, <hi>Sed propter hoc data ſunt ſignaquae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, &amp;c:</hi> but for all this there are manifeſt ſignes and tokens of ſalvation, that it is without all doubt that hee is of the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Elect, in whom thoſe tokens doe remaine.</p>
               <p>Of which tokens or ſignes he ſpeaketh thus in another place,<note place="margin">In Octav. Paſc. Serm. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Quomodo ſine teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monio electos ſuos deſerat Deus?</hi> How ſhould God leaue his Elect without teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony? (of their election) or what com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort might there bee vnto them floting carefully betwixt hope and feare, if they did not finde the favour to haue ſome te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony thereof? The Lord knoweth who are his, he onely knoweth whom he hath choſen from the beginning; but what man knoweth, if hee be worthy of loue or hatred? But if, as certaine it is,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:20803:55"/>that certainety be deemed vnto vs,<note place="margin">The certainety of faith is gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from ſuch ſignes &amp; tokens as by the Word of God are deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered vnto vs, &amp; according to Saint Bernard are ſuch as doe keepe vs from that wauing &amp; wandring, which otherwiſe might bee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt hope and feare. <hi>Idem de E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vang. ſeptem panis Serm. 3.</hi>
                  </note> how much the more delightfull ſhall they bee, if we can finde any tokens of this electio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? For what reſt can our ſoule haue, ſo long as it hath no teſtimony of its owne prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtination? Therefore it is a word to bee beleeved, and worthy by al meanes to be received, whereby the witneſſe and teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of our ſaluation is commended vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs.</p>
               <p>Further, ſpeaking of the ſeuenth Loafe. and the three peeces belonging vnto it: &amp; expreſſing this certainety in himſelf ſaith, <hi>Septimus quo<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> panis eſt ſpes obtinendi, cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ius nihilominus teneo fragmenta tria, &amp; co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ſapor dulcis admodum gutturi meo.</hi> The ſeuenth Loafe ſaith he, is <hi>hope of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining pardon for my ſin;</hi> of which Loafe I hold three pieces, the taſte of which is very ſweet to my throat. There be three I ſay, which doe ſo ſtrengthen and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme my heart, as that no want of merits, no conſideration of mine owne vileneſſe, no eſtimation of the heavenly bliſſe can caſt mee downe from the height of my hope being faſt rooted therein.<note place="margin">Saint Bernard affirmeth a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of faith, built, not vpon his owne imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate knowledge and apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but vpon the loue of God in adopting him the truth of his promiſe, and his power to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme the ſame.</note> Theſe 3 I ſay, wherein my hope wholly conſiſteth
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:20803:56"/>
                  <hi>charitatem adoptionis, veritatem promiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onis, poteſtatem redditionis;</hi> the loue of God in adopting me; the truth of his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe; &amp; his power to performe the ſame. Let my fooliſh thought now repine and murmure as much as it will, ſaying, Who art thou, and how great is that glory; and by what merits doeſt thou hope to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the ſame? &amp; I will boldly anſwere. I know whom I haue beleeved, and I am certaine and ſure of it, becauſe he hath a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dopted me in great loue, becauſe he is true in his promiſe, and becauſe he is of power to make good the ſame.</p>
               <p>Further.<note place="margin">Serm. 8. in Cant.</note> 
                  <hi>Quae in vobis anima ſenſit ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quando in ſecreto conſcientiae ſuae ſpiritum filij clamantem, Abba Pater, Ipſa, ipſapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terno ſe diligi affectu praeſumat, quae eodem ſe ſpiritu, quo &amp; filius affectam ſentit, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fide quaecun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> es illa, confide nihil haſitans.</hi> What ſoule amongſt you ſoever doth ſometime feele in the ſecret of his conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, the ſpirit of the ſonne, crying <hi>Abba</hi> Father; that ſoule, euen that ſoule may preſume that it is beloued with a Fatherly affection, which doth feele it ſelfe belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by the ſame ſpirit, that the ſonne is;
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:20803:56"/>bee bold how foule ſoever thou art, bee bold, doubting nothing at all. In the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of the ſon, acknowledge thy ſelfe to bee the daughter of the wife and ſiſter of the ſon. <hi>Non est quod iam talis anima di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere vereatur, dilectus meus mihi:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In Cant. 69. Serm.</note> 
                  <hi>quod ex eo quod ſe diligere, &amp; vehementer diligere ſentit, etiam diligi nihilominus vehementer non ambigit, ac de ſua ſingulari intentione, ſolicitudine, cura, opera, diligentia ſtudio<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> quo inceſſanter &amp; ardenter invigilat quem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>admodum placeat Deo, aeque haec omnia in ipſo indubitanter agnoſcit, recordans pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſionis eius; Ergo ex proprijs, quae ſunt pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes Deum agnoſcit, nec dubitat ſe amari, qui amat.</hi> There is now no occaſion that ſuch a ſoule ſhould be afraid to ſay, <hi>my Welbeloved is mine,</hi> which out of that, that it perceiveth it ſelf to loue, &amp; vehemently to loue, doth nothing doubt, but that it is beloved againe vehemently; &amp; out of its owne ſpeciall diligence, care, ſtudy, inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, whereby it doth earneſtly &amp; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out intermiſſion take good heed, how it may pleaſe God, it doth vndoubtedly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge all theſe things to be in him, remembring his promiſe. Therefore from
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:20803:57"/>thoſe things which are properly Gods it doth acknowledge, nor at all doubt, but that it is beloved, which doth loue.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mens quae divino Spiritu impletur,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Greg. dial. lib. 1. cap. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>hà<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet evidentiſſima ſua ſigna, virtutes ſcilieet &amp; humilitatem, quae ſi utra<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> perfectè in u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namente conveniant, liquet quod de prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentia Spiritus Sancti teſtimonium ferant.</hi> The mind that is filled with the holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, hath its moſt evident ſignes &amp; toke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, that is to wit, grace and humility, both which if they meet together in one ſoule, it is certaine, that they beare witneſſe of the preſence of the holy Ghoſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Deum ſitiens anima prius timore com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pungitur,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Greg. lib. 6. regiſtri c. 187.</note> 
                  <hi>poſt amore &amp;c. at verò quum lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ga moeroris anxietate fuerit formido con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumpta<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> quaedam iam de preſumptione veniae naſcitur ſecuritas.</hi> The ſoule that thirſteth after God, is firſt pricked with feare, then with loue; but when feare through long heavineſſe of ſorrow ſhalbe conſumed, there is then a certaine ſecurity bred of obtaining mercy.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iuſtiviri ſecuritas recte Leoni compara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Greg. Moral. lib. 31. cap. 23.</note> 
                  <hi>quia contra ſe cum quoſlibet iuſurgere conspicit, ad mentis ſuae confidentiam redit:
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:20803:57"/>&amp; ſcit quia cunctos adverſantes ſuperat, quia illum ſolum diligit, quem invitus nullo modo amittat.</hi> The co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fidence of a iuſt man may rightly be compared to a Lion; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe when he ſeeth any to riſe vp againſt him, retireth to the aſſurance of his owne mind, &amp; knoweth that he doth overcome all that oppoſe, becauſe he onely loueth him, whom vnwillingly by no meanes he may loſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>There is no inherent righteouſneſſe in man, whereby he may be iuſtified before Gods Tribunall; But the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt is imputed being apprehended by faith.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quòd ſi dixerit, Patertuus addixit te, respondebo, ſed frater meus redemit me,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bern. Epiſt. 190.</note> 
                  <hi>cur non aliundè iustitia, cum aliundè reatus? Alius qui peccatorem constituit, alius qui iuſtificat à peccato, alter in ſemine, alter in ſanguine. An peccatu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in ſemine peccatoris, &amp; non iuſtitia, in Chriſti ſanguine? ſed iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitia. inquiet, ſi cuius eſt, quid ad te? Eſto, ſed ſit etiam culpa cuius eſt, quid ad me? An
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:20803:58"/>iuſtitia iuſti ſuper eum erit, &amp; impiet as im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pij non erit ſuper eum?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Adam bound vs. Chriſt hath ſet vs free. The matter of our condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is in Adam, and the matter of our ſalvation is in Chriſt: ſo that Bernard heere plainely affirmeth both the imputation of Adams ſin to condemnation, and the imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Chriſts righteouſneſſe accordingly to iuſtification. The Rhemiſts in their notes on the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment do nothing ſo much as mock &amp; ſcoffe at this doctrine of the imputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Chriſts righteouſnes; blasphemouſly calling it, a new no iuſtice a phan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſticall apprehenſion of that which is not, a falſe faith and vntrue impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation. in Rom. <hi>3.</hi> verſe <hi>22.</hi> we are not onely by acceptation or imputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on partakers of Chriſts benefites, but are by his grace made worthy thereof, and deſerue our ſalvation condignely. Col. <hi>1,</hi> v. <hi>13.</hi> in margine. this is lofty &amp; hye doctrine, and worthy the buskin, but far from S. Bernards humility.</note> But if he ſhall ſay, thy father hath bound thee over, I wil an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, but my brother hath redeemed me. Why ſhould not righteouſneſſe bee of an other, ſeeing guilt is of another? It was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother that made me a ſinner, it is another that iuſtifieth from ſinne, the one in his ſeed, the other in his bloud. Is there ſin in the ſeed of a ſinner, and is there not righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe in the Blood of Chriſt? But he will ſay, if there be a righteouſneſſe of any ones, what is that to thee? Let it be ſo. But then let the fault be whoſe it is, what is that to me? Shall the righteouſneſſe of the righteous be vpon himſelfe, and ſhall not the wickedneſſe of the wicked be v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon himſelfe? It is not meete that the ſon ſhould beare the iniquity of the father, &amp; be denied to be partaker of the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his brother.</p>
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:20803:58"/>
               <p>And before in the ſame Epiſtle, <hi>Aſſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nata eſt homini aliena iuſtitia, quia caruit ſua, nam ſi unus pro omnibus mortuus eſt, ergo omnes mortui ſunt: ut videlicet ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factio unius omnibus imputetur, ſicut omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vm peccata unus ille portavit.</hi> There is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to man, an other mans righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe; becauſe he wanted his owne. For if one did die for all, then all were dead, that ſo the ſatisfactio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of one, might be imputed to all, even as that one did beare the ſinnes of all.</p>
               <p>Againe.<note place="margin">In Cant. ſerm. 61. Geneſ. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>Et ideo liquet erraſſe illum qui ait Maior eſt iniquitas mea, quam ut vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ammerear, niſi quod non erat de membris Chriſti, nec pertinebat ad eum de merito Chriſti, ut ſuum preſumeret, ſuum diceret quod illius eſſet, tanquam rem capitis mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brum.</hi> And therefore he did erre who ſaid, <hi>My ſin is greater than it can be forgiuen,</hi> &amp; he ſpake it in that hee was not one of the members of Chriſt, neither did any thing pertaine vnto him of the merit of Chriſt, that he ſhould preſume it was his,<note place="margin">The righteouſnes that is aſſigned vnto us, is an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and not our owne.</note> or that he could ſay, that was his which was Chriſts, as a member of the riches of the Head.</p>
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:20803:59"/>
               <p>After, <hi>Domine memorabor iuſtitiae tua ſolius. Ipſa eſt enim &amp; mea, nempe factus es mihi in iuſtitìa à Deo. Numquid mihi vere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum ne non una ambobus ſufficiat? non eſt pallium breve quod non poſſit operire duos. Iuſtitia tua iuſtitia in aeternum. Quid lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gius aeternitate, &amp; te pariter, &amp; me operiet largiter largae &amp; aeterna iuſtitia. Et in me quidem operit multitudinem peccatorùm, in te autem Dominé quid niſi pietatis theſau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ros divina bonitatis?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Here is no men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of inherent righteouſneſſe, but onely of Chriſts righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes imputed, apprehended by faith.</note> O Lord, I will reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber thy righteouſneſſe alone, for that is mine alſo; for thou art made vnto mee righteouſnes by God. And ſhall I feare that one righteouſnes will not ſerve two? It is not a ſhort Cloke (as the Prophet faith) ſuch as cannot cover two. Thy righteouſneſſe is righteouſneſſe for ever. What is longer than eternity. Thy large and everlaſting righteouſneſſe will cover both thee &amp; me fully, in me it will indeed cover a multitude of ſinnes; but in thee O Lord what but the Treaſures of Piety, the riches of goodneſſe.</p>
               <p>Again,<note place="margin">In Cant. ſerm. 25.</note> vpon that ſpeech of the Church, <hi>Niger ſum, ſed formoſa, filia Hieruſalem.</hi> I am blacke. but welfavoured, daughter
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:20803:59"/>of Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſaith, <hi>Videamus iam quid illud fuerit dicere, nigraſum, ſed formoſa. Nulla ne in his verbis repugnantia eſt? Abſit, non omne quod nigrum eſt, continuò deforme eſt, &amp;c.</hi> Let vs ſee what it is to ſay, I am blacke, but comely,<note place="margin">This is the beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the church, not her being without ſin, but remiſſion and forgiueneſſe of ſinnes by the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt, imputed vnto it, &amp; ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended by faith: ſo that as the Church is blacke, but faire through Chriſt, ſo Chriſt is faire in himſelfe, but he ſeemed blacke for the Churches ſake. Eſay <hi>53.</hi>
                  </note> Is there no repugna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie in theſe words? God forbid. Every thing that is blacke, is not ſtraightwayes ill-favoured. Blackneſſe (for example) in the ball of the eye is not vncomely, and ſome blacke haires ſerue for ornament. After this manner perhaps may the Bride (or Church) with the beauty truly of her feature, not want her mole or ſpot of blacknes, but then it is in the time of her pilgrimage. It ſhall bee otherwiſe in her country, when the Bridegroome of glory ſhall make her to himſelfe a glorious Church, not having ſpot or wrinckle, or any ſuch thing. But now if ſhe ſhould ſay, ſhe hath no blacknes, ſhe ſhould deceive her ſelfe, and there were no truth in her.</p>
               <p>And to the ſame effect hee ſaith elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>In Cant. ſerm. 38.</hi> The Church is but begun in this life to purged from iniquity, &amp; framed in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part therefrom: &amp; ſo is every one that is iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified by faith in Chriſt, having Chriſts righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe imputed vnto him: <hi>In Cantie. 38. Serm.</hi>
                  </note> ſhewing how the Church (or Bride is ſaid <hi>to bee faire among weomen, Spiritualis autem anima, &amp;c.</hi> The ſpiritual ſoule although it be now ſo far faire, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:20803:60"/>it walketh not according to the fleſh, but according to the ſpirit. But yet in reſpect that it continueth in this body, it doth tend to the perfection of fairenes, and therefore is not at all hands faire, but faire among weomen, that is, in reſpect of earthly mindes, &amp; thoſe that are not ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall, as ſhe is. <hi>Tunc audies. Tota pulchra es amica mea, &amp; macula non eſt in te. Nunc vero etſi ex parte iam ſimilis, ex parte tame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tamen diſſimilis &amp;c. ſed &amp; ego te dico pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chram, ſed inter mulieres, id est, ex parte.</hi> Then (that is in the Countrey of Heaven) thou ſhalt heare theſe words, <hi>Thou art all faire my Loue,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Partly faire and partly black: the white garment of Chriſt muſt cover this black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</note> and there is no ſpot in thee. But now although thou art in part like, yet in part thou art vnlike. I ſay thou art faire, but it is among weomen, that is to ſay, in part.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Touching the lawfulneſſe of mariages in Miniſters where the gift of continency is not giuen.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tinam qui continere non valent, perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionem temerariè profiteri,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Deconverſ. ad Cleric. ſerm. 29.</note> 
                  <hi>aut coelebatui dare nomina verentur.</hi> Would to God that
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:20803:60"/>thoſe that cannot containe would ſtand in awe to profeſſe ſingle life: for doubtles it were much better to marry then to burne. But there are many, and ſo many, that they cannot bee hid for multitude, &amp; for impudency do not ſeeke it, who vſe their libertie, as an occaſion to the fleſh, abſtaining from marriage, and flowing from thence into all manner of filthines, fornication, adulteries, inceſts, Sodome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and that which filthy Sodome never knew.</p>
               <p>And touching thoſe that haue vowed a right vow (ſuppoſe chaſtitie) and finde they cannot containe, or performe it, the bond is not abſolute, but of conditionall neceſſitie. <hi>Ego non arbitror minora vota impedire maiora,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Epiſt. 47.</note> 
                  <hi>nec Deum exigère quod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> bonum ſibi promiſſum, ſi pro ea meli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us aliquod perſolutum.</hi> I doe not thinke (ſaith he) that leſſer vowes can hinder the greater, neither that God doth require, every good that is promiſed him, if for thoſe any thing better ſhallbee paid him, &amp;c. <hi>In turpi voto muta decretum,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lib. 5. ad ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rorem.</note> In a filthy vow, change thy minde.</p>
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:20803:61"/>
               <p>Againe.<note place="margin">In Cant. ſerm. 66.</note> 
                  <hi>Tolle de Eccleſia honorabile co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nubium, &amp; thorum immaculatum: nonne reples eam concubinarijs, inceſtuoſis, ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifluis, mollibus, maſculorum concubitori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, &amp; omni deni<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> genere immundorum?</hi> Take from the Church honorable marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, &amp; the vndefiled bed; and doeſt thou not fill it with keepers of concubines, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtuous perſons, ſeed-looſers, &amp; all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of vncleane perſons.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>There is no fleſhly and orall eating of the naturall body of Chriſt in the Sacrament, neither doe the wicked eate him at all.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cum audirent dicentem,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In Pſalm. qui habitat. ſerm. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>niſi manduca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veritis carnem filij hominis, &amp; biberitis e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ius ſanguinem dixerunt. &amp;c.</hi> When they heard him ſay, Except you eate the fleſh of the Sonne of man, &amp; drinke his blood. They ſaid,<note place="margin">This is that which wee call the eating of Chriſts fleſh, and drinking of hish loud.</note> it is an hard ſaying, and they went from him. But what is it to eate his fieſh and drinke his blood, except to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member his ſufferings, and to imitat that converſation, which he led in the fieſh?
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:20803:61"/>whereto hee appointed that pure Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the altar where wee receaue the Lords body, that as the forme of bread doth ſeeme to enter into vs; ſo wee ſhall knowe by the converſation which he had in the fleſh that hee doth enter into vs to dwell in our hearts by faith.</p>
               <p>Againe. <hi>Sacramentum dicitur ſacrum</hi> ſignum,<note place="margin">Inſerm. de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>ſive ſacrum ſecretum. Multa qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem fiunt propter ſe tantum; alia vero prop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter alia deſignanda, &amp; ipſa dicuntur &amp; ſunt ſigna.</hi> A Sacrament is ſaid to bee an holy ſigne, or an holy ſecret.<note place="margin">The nature of a ſigne doth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſt in ſetting forth another thing.</note> But many ſignes are ordained for themſelues onely, yet ſome ſignes are ordained for other things &amp; thoſe are called, and ſo are ſignes. That therefore we may take example from vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all things. A ring is given as a ring abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutly, in that there is no ſimilitude.<note place="margin">A viſible ſigne is like a ring, or an earneſt peny.</note> It is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven alſo to inveſt one into an inheritance &amp; then it is a ſigne; ſo that hee that recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth the ring may now ſay. <hi>The ring avai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth nothing,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Grace is conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered in respect of thoſe that vſe it; not that it is really in the ſignes.</note> 
                  <hi>but it is the inheritance that I ſeeke.</hi> In the ſame manner our Lord ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching neere to his paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, tooke care that his (members) ſhould bee clothed with his grace, that the inviſible grace
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:20803:62"/>might be exhibited by ſome viſible ſigne. To this purpoſe are all Sacraments inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted, to this purpoſe was the receauing of the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> and <hi>Chriſme;</hi> to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe alſo was <hi>Baptiſme,</hi> the beginning of all Sacraments; in which wee are planted together with him into the likeneſſe of his death. For as in outward things there are divers ſignes,<note place="margin">Theſe examples fight directly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall preſence and yee proue with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, that the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments are not bare ſignes. In ſerm. de pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rificat. The Prieſt alone doth not conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crate nor ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, but the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple with him: therefore there is no reall tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation of the bread into the body of Chriſt, nor reall ſacrifice of that body.</note> that we may tarry vpon the example firſt taken. There are many ornaments wherewith wee are adorned, for example, a Biſhop by his ſtaffe, and his ring. As it is in theſe things, ſo are the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſities of gifts deliuered in divers Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments.</p>
               <p>Againe. <hi>Neque enim credere debemus quod ſoli ſacerdoti ſupra dictae virtutes ſint neceſſariae &amp;c.</hi> Neither (ſaith he) ought we to beleeue, that thoſe fore recited ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues belone only to the Prieſts: <hi>as though he alone did conſecrate and ſacrifice the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Chriſt;</hi> Hee doth not ſacrifice alone, hee doth not conſecrate alone, but the whole company of the faithfull which ſtand by, doe conſecrate &amp; ſacrifice with him. Therefore the ſtanders by ought to haue of their owne, as well as the Prieſt,
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:20803:62"/>
                  <hi>firme faith, pure prayer, godly devotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> And in the ſame ſermon expounding the Text of S. Paul, <hi>The cup of bleſſing which wee bleſſe &amp;c.</hi> ſaith, Heare bretheren, not mee but the Apoſtle, <hi>The cup of bleſſing which we bleſſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">This is the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed end of theſe myſteries; there is a ſecret diſpenſation of grace in their vſe, that is a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and bloud of Chriſt: but this inferreth not, nor doth the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery require that the truth meant in the myſteries, ſhould by any corporall preſence be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, or lye hid vnder the ſigner. In caena domini.</note> 
                  <hi>is it not the communio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the blood of Chriſt?</hi> The cup, that is to ſay, the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking of the cup maketh vs to haue a certaine fellowſhip with Chriſt: And the bread which we breake is it not a parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the body of Chriſt? As if hee ſhould ſay, the bread which wee breake maketh vs one body vnder Chriſt our head; becauſe as one bread is made of ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny cornes, which afterward is turned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the body of Chriſt, <hi>both by faith,</hi> and by the holy words which Chriſt taught his <hi>(Church)</hi> ſo, many participating of that body in the vnitie of <hi>faith, hope, and charitie,</hi> are one body with Chriſt.</p>
               <p>In his next tract of the Lords ſupper ſpeaking plentifully of this argument a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt many other, he hath theſe words, <hi>In hoc Sacramento, no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſolum quaelibet gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia, ſed ille à quo eſt omnis gratia ſumitur.</hi> In this Sacrament (ſaith he) not only eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry grace, but he fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whom all grace flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:20803:63"/>is had. For Chriſt was once made a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving oblation for the life of the world, a generall reconciliation, and gaue to all Sacraments as well thoſe of the old Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, as of the new, <hi>vertue and efficacy that by ſuch and ſo great an offering,</hi> all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> might be ſanctified that were to beſaued. He is the lamb ſlaine from the beginning of the world, that is, to the faithfull that were from the beginning; And in that it is ſaid, from the beginning, not the time of his death is ſet forth,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prins enim mors cius pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit quam fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it.</hi> If Chriſt ſpake of the bread, as certainely he did and S. Bernard acknowledgeth, then ſinely tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation is vtterly over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwne, as all Papiſts knowe, that knowe the difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene them &amp; vs.</note> but of his bringing ſalvation. For his death did profit before it was. After deſcribing the order of the adminiſtratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Lords ſupper. Chriſt (ſaith he) ſpake of the bread, ſaying, <hi>Take eate, this is my body,</hi> and ſo of the wine, <hi>drinke you all of this,</hi> this is my blood which ſhall bee ſhed for many to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſinnes. Now touching the <hi>effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacie</hi> and <hi>communion</hi> of the body &amp; blood of Chriſt; We (ſaith he) are knit in an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable vnion with Chriſt, and Chriſt with vs, as he himſelfe ſaith, <hi>he that eateth my fleſh and drinketh my blood, remaineth in mee, and I in him.</hi> And this is to bee thought of thoſe that receaue worthily,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:20803:63"/>and not of the wicked. Surely at one ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, at the Lords ſupper, <hi>Iudas</hi> and <hi>Peter</hi> receaued both one conſecrated bread; <hi>Peter</hi> to life, <hi>Iudas</hi> to damnation. And vpon the words, <hi>Hoc facite in meam com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memorationem.</hi> Doe this in remembrance of me. Hee mentioneth <hi>no reall ſacrifice of Chriſts body and bloud,</hi> ſuch as is made in the Maſſe; <hi>But a thank full remembrance of his death and paſſion. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>oluit Chriſtus ve iugiter coleretur per misterium, quod ſemel efferebatur in precium, &amp; illa perennis vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctima viveret in memoria,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Loe! the death of Chriſt is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies preſent in grace, away with the maſſe then.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp; praefens eſſet ſemper in gratia.</hi> Chriſt appointed that he ſhould be alwaies worſhipped in a myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, becauſe <hi>He was once offered for redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and that everlaſting offering ſhould liue in memory, <hi>and bee alwaies preſent in grace,</hi> nay it is a ſufficient medicine for all,<note place="margin">Here he plainely divideth remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance from pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, attribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the one to this life whereins we be, and the other to the life to come. <hi>2.</hi> Cor. <hi>5.7.</hi>
                  </note> if through <hi>faith</hi> and <hi>imitation</hi> the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of his forepaſſed death be kept. <hi>No<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> enim pariomnino iucunditate ſumitur cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tex ſacramenti &amp; medulla frumenti &amp;c. Hic pereat phyſicale nutrimentum. Cibus iſte no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt ventris ſed mentis.</hi> The outward barke of the Sacrament, is not receaued with like pleaſure, as the fatneſſe of the
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:20803:64"/>corne, faith &amp; ſhew, memory &amp; preſence, eternitre &amp; time, the viſage &amp; the glaſſe, the image of God, and the faſhion of a ſervant. But here we walke by <hi>faith,</hi> and not by ſight. In the meane time we ought to take delight and reioice, in the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the altar, in the making whereof <hi>the faithfull miniſter</hi> doth finde himſelfe in the midſt of the <hi>Father, Sonne, and holy Ghoſt;</hi> the higher orders ſtanding about on every ſide. Here let naturall nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ceaſe. This is meat, not for the belly but for the ſoule.</p>
               <p>To conclude, <hi>Sacramentum enim, ſine re ſacramenti niors eſt ſumenti.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Vt ſupra in ſer. de coma.</note> 
                  <hi>Res vero ſacramenti etiam praeter ſacramentum vita aeterna eſt accipienti.</hi> The Sacrament with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the thing of the Sacrament,<note place="margin">Speake Papiſt. Tell plainely, what is the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, &amp; the thing of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, &amp; how the body of Chriſt can bee eaten even with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?</note> is death to the receauer; but the thing of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, even without the Sacrament, is everlaſting life to the receauer. As often as thou art godly and faithfully affected, and devoted to imitate Chriſt in comme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moration of him who ſuffered for thee, thou eateſt his body, &amp; drinkeſt his bloud and as long as thou remaineſt in him by loue, thou ſhalt be counted vnto him by
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:20803:64"/>the working of righteouſneſſe and boly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in thee, of his body and of his mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>S. Bernard perſwadeth Pope Euge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius from clayming tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall iuriſdiction.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>PRopheta cum ait (vt evellas, &amp; deſtruas;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">De conſider: ad Eugen. lib. <hi>2.</hi> Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem, cap. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>&amp; disperdas &amp; diſſipes, &amp; adifices &amp; plantes) quid horum faſtum ſonat?</hi> The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Ieremy</hi> ſaith. Behold I haue appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted thee over nations, to plucke vp, &amp; to root out, and to deſtroy, &amp; throw downe, to build &amp; to plant: which of theſe words doe ſavour of pride? nay rather <hi>the spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall labour is expreſſed</hi> by termes bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed of from husbandmen. And wee therefore may perceaue, there is much gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vs in charge, <hi>a miniſtry,</hi> not <hi>a rule,</hi> Let it be that you are a Prophet, but are you more then a Prophet? But if you be wiſe, you will bee content with that meaſure, which God hath allotted vnto you, for what is more proceedeth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> evill. Learne by the example of the Prophet, <hi>to haue a charge; not ſo much to Lord it,</hi> as to prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:20803:65"/>that which the time requireth.</p>
               <p>In his 42 <hi>Epistle,</hi> thus hee writeth <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligit is quae dico? &amp;c.</hi> Doe you vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand what I ſay? Let honour be giuen to whom honour belongeth. Let every ſoul (ſaith the Apoſtle) be ſubiect to the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er powers. If every ſoule, then yours; for who hath excepted you, from this gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality. If any man doth indeavour to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept you fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the obedience of the Prince, he deceaueth you. Doe not reſt on their counſells, for notwithſtanding they are Chriſtians, yet they thinke ſcorne, either to follow Chriſts deeds, or obey Chriſts words. Thoſe are they that ſay vnto you <hi>Maintaine Sir the honour of your Sea,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">There were flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers of the Pope in S. Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nards time, and haue they bani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed them ſince?</note> 
                  <hi>&amp;c are not you ſo good as your predeceſſours?</hi> If your Sea be not advanced by you, yet let it not be abaſed by you. <hi>Haec iſti.</hi> Thus ſay they. But Chriſt both taught and did far otherwiſe; for he ſaith, <hi>Giue to Caeſar the the things that belong to Caeſar, and giue to God the things that belong to God,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Lib. <hi>1.</hi> de conſid. ad Eugenium.</note>In his booke of Conſideration written purpoſely to the Pope himſelfe, hee hath divers paſſages to this ſame effect. <hi>In cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minibus, non in poſſeſſionibus poteſt as veſtra
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:20803:65"/>&amp;c.</hi> Your power (ſaith he) is touching of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences, and not poſſeſſions, becauſe you receaued the keyes of the kingdome of heauen, to deale in the one but not in the other, ſhutting out offenders, but not poſſeſſioners, that you might know (ſaith Chriſt) that the ſonne of man hath power in earth to forgiue ſinnes &amp;c. Which doth ſeeme vnto you, the greater dignitie, and power; to for giue ſinnes, or to divide in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritances? But there is no compariſon. Thoſe meane and inferiour things haue their Iudges, Kings, and Princes of the earth. Why doe you invade other mens bounds, why doe you put your ſickle in other mens corne?</p>
               <p>Againe in his third book,<note place="margin">Lib. <hi>3.</hi> de conſ. ad Eugen. Pſ. <hi>49</hi>
                  </note> he hath theſe words <hi>Non tu ille de quo Propheta. Et erit omnis terra poſſeſſio tius &amp;c.</hi> You are not he of whom the Prophet ſpake <hi>And all the earth ſhall be his poſſeſſion. It is Chriſt who challengeth it for his poſſeſſion.</hi> To who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> but to him is it ſaid?<note place="margin">Pſal. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> Aske of me and I wil giue thee the heathen for thine inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, &amp; the vttermoſt parts of the earth for thy poſſeſſion. Giue Chriſt the poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and Lordſhip, take you the care of it.
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:20803:66"/>This is your part, ſtretch not your ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny further. Yea, but you will ſay, Thou denieſt me not to be aboue others;<note place="margin">Non negas prae eſſe, et do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minari vetas? Plane ſic.</note> and doſt thou deny me to haue ſoveraigntie? indeed even ſo. Who gouerneth by ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king care; you are exalted to profit others you gouerne as a faithfull wiſe ſervant, <hi>whom the Lord hath ſet over his family.</hi> But to what end?<note place="margin">Preach the word depoſe noe prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</note> 
                  <hi>that you may giue them meat in due ſeaſon.</hi> That is, to diſtribute the meat, not to command with authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</p>
               <p>And in the fourth booke ſpeaking (as before) of thoſe flatterers, that belike were very neere him, and therefore very likely to thruſt too much greatneſſe on him, ſaith, <hi>A te tamen mos iſte, vel potius mors ista non coepit, in te vtinam deſinat.</hi> But they ſay, this cuſtome, or rather this deſtruction began not in you, I would yet it might end in you. Doe you not ſee, that all your Eccleſiaſticall zeale &amp; care ſtandeth only in maintenance of honours vpon honour all is beſtowed; vpon holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, either nothing or very little. If vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on occaſion you would ſomewhat ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit your ſelfe and deale familiarly. <hi>O doe
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:20803:66"/>not ſo, ſay they, it is not meet:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Thus doe the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits ſchoole his holines at Rome now.</note> 
                  <hi>it is not agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the time, it is not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>venient for your maieſtie. Conſider well what ſtate you heare.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And in the ſecond booke,<note place="margin">lib. 2. de conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</note> ſpeaking of worldly honour and wealth, and pompe, ſaith. <hi>Nihil horum tabula teſtatoris adſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>navit:</hi> None of thoſe doth the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures allow or giue you. But what? If you be content with their evidence, you ſhall rather inherit <hi>care and paines,</hi> then <hi>Glory and riches. Blanditur cathedra?</hi> Doth your chaire flatter you? you are in a watchtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,<note place="margin">Inde denique ſuperintendis.</note> from thence you carefully looke over all, the name of Biſhop ſounding vnto you not Lordſhip, but ſervice. <hi>Planum eſt Apoſtolis interdicitur dominatus.</hi> It is plaine, that ſoveraigntie was forbidden the Apoſtles; take heed therefore that you vſurpe not, either as a Lord the Apoſtle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, or as being Apoſtolike, Lordſhip, becauſe you are forbidden both. If you will haue both alike, you ſhal looſe both. Otherwiſe doe not take your ſelfe to bee exempted from the number of thoſe, of whom the Lord God doth thus com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine, <hi>They haue raigned, but not by mee.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hoſea. cap. <hi>8.</hi> verſ. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <pb n="110" facs="tcp:20803:67"/>
                  <hi>They were Princes, but I knewe them, not.</hi> But if it further any thing to rule, without God, you haue glory, but not with God. <hi>The Apostolike forme is this, ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraigntie is forbidden; ſervice is comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In his Epiſtle vnto <hi>Lewis</hi> the younger King of France,<note place="margin">Ad Ludonicu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> iuniorem Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gem Francoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> epiſt. 170.</note> thus he writeth, <hi>Si totus orbis adverſum me coniuraret, &amp;c.</hi> If the whole world (ſaith he) ſhould conſpire together againſt me, that I ſhould vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take any thing againſt the Kings authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, yet would I haue God in my mind, and durſt not fooliſhly doe any thing againſt the king who is ordeined by him. Neither am I ignorant where it is that I reade, <hi>He that reſiſteth the power, reſisteth the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of God</hi> And after ſome expoſtulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of matters that then went not well, he addeth, This truth ſhall never be leſſened in vs, <hi>The honour of the King &amp; the profit of his Kingdome ſhall neuer bee impaired by vs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the 45. Epiſtle,<note place="margin">Epiſt. 45. ad Ludou. regem Francor.</note> 
                  <hi>Stephan</hi> the Abbot of Ciſtercenſe, writing to the ſame <hi>Lewis</hi> thus, <hi>Rex coeli &amp; terrae regnum vobis in terra donavit, donaturus &amp; in coelo, ſi id
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:20803:67"/>quod accepiſtis, iuſtè &amp; ſapienter admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrare ſtudueritis.</hi> The King of Heauen &amp; earth,<note place="margin">Then doe not Princes holde their ſcepters of the Pope.</note> hath given you a Kingdome vpon earth, and will giue you one in Heaven, if you doe endeavour to governe that, iuſtly and wiſely which you haue recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of him.<note place="margin">Doe you conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der when you pleaſe, O ye Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, by teaching the contrary do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine? not the Lord of Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe, but the Pope of Rome. <hi>Epiſt. 221.</hi> If ſoveraigne Maieſty ſhould doe any thing to the Churches de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triment, either in oppreſſing it, or winking at the oppreſſing thereof: Saint Bernard in this caſe will not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble the wrongs of his mother, but would take armes, yet ſuch as ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the Lords Prieſt, Chriſts Champion, and the Churches Child, Prayers and teares pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red out to God.</note> 
                  <hi>Attenditis iam cui &amp; ex hoc infenſum vos redditis?</hi> Doe you conſider whom you haue offended and diſpleaſed by this deede of yours? Verily, not the Biſhop of Paris, but the Lord of Paradiſe, who is to be feared, who taketh away the liues of the Princes.</p>
               <p>To conclude all, I finde in the 221. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle to the ſame king <hi>Lewis</hi> theſe words, <hi>At quicquid vobis de regno veſtro de ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma &amp; corona veſtra facere placeat: nos Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae filij, &amp;c.</hi> But howſoever it pleaſe you to eſteeme of your life, crowne, and dignity: yet wee that are ſonnes of the Church, cannot at any hand, hide the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts, wrongs, and the treading vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foot of our mother. <hi>Profectò ſtabimus &amp; pugnabimus uſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ad mortem, ſi ita oportue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit pro matre noſtra, armis, quibus licet, non ſcutis &amp; gladijs, ſed precibus, fletibus<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ad Deum.</hi> Surely we wil ſtand and fight even
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:20803:68"/>vnto death, if it were expedient, for our mother (the Church) with ſuch weapons as is fitting not with ſwords &amp; bucklers; but with prayers and teares powred out to God.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of vnwritten Traditions which the Councell of Trent, made e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual with the written word of God.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epiſt. 91. ad Abbates Suiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſione congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatos.</hi> If the Councell of Trent had bin thus religious, they would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver haue equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Traditions vnwritten, with the written Word of God, nor have fathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red their maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing ceremonies &amp; veſtments on the Tradition of the Apoſtles, ſuch as the miter, the ſtole, the albe, amice, girdle, chiſible, and fane.</note>
                  <hi>Adiſtud concilium toto deſiderio feror in quo traditiones, &amp;c.</hi> I haue an exceeding great deſire to bee at a Councell where <hi>Traditions</hi> may not be obſtinately defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, nor ſuperſtitiouſly obſerved, but where it may be with diligence &amp; humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity inquired, what the good, &amp; accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and perfect will of God is. Let them depart from you &amp; from me, that ſay, wee will not bee better than our Fathers. Ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we muſt aſcend, or deſcend. If thou wilt ſtand ſtill, thou muſt needes fall. Hee is not good, that will not be better; and when thou wilt not become better, then
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:20803:68"/>thou beginneſt to grow worſe.</p>
               <p>Againe, <hi>Nonne iuſtiſſimum eſſe liquet,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">De praec. &amp; diſpenſat. pag. 290. a. fine.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp;c.</hi> doth it not appeare moſt iuſt (ſaith he) that thoſe things, which were ordei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for charitie, may for charitie alſo where it ſeemeth neceſſarie, be either o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted or deferred, or peradventure bee changed more commodiouſly into a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.<note place="margin">If thoſe traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which are brought in for a good intent, may be laide a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide: how much more the Church of Rome of its owne accord thruſteth vpon the Church of God.</note> As on the other ſide, it would be out of doubt very vniuſt, if thoſe things which were ordeined for meere charitie, ſhould be retained againſt charitie; but whatſoever is ordeined by God, is not to be violated or broken. And then citing Pope <hi>Gelaſius,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Vbi neceſſitas non eſt, inconvertibilia maneant patrum ſancto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum decreta.</hi> Where neceſſitie doth not require, let the decrees of the holy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers remaine vntouched. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bitamen Deo contraria non praecipit homo,</hi> but it is where man doth not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maund contrary things to God. For where the authenticall ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures doe ſpeake, wee muſt there neither looke for a commaunder, nor hearken to a forbidder.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
